<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sufficiencie of the spirits teaching, without humane-learning: or A treatise, tending to proue humane-learning to be no help to the spirituall understanding of the Word of God. Written (if it may be) for the silencing of such false and scandalous reports, as have been rumored about concerning this matter; and also for the affording of true information to all such as desire to know the truth. By Samuel How</title>
            <author>How, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 891:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sufficiencie of the spirits teaching, without humane-learning: or A treatise, tending to proue humane-learning to be no help to the spirituall understanding of the Word of God. Written (if it may be) for the silencing of such false and scandalous reports, as have been rumored about concerning this matter; and also for the affording of true information to all such as desire to know the truth. By Samuel How</title>
                  <author>How, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Seen, allowed, and printed, by us &amp;c. [at the Cloppenburg Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:1"/>
            <p>THE SVFFICIENCIE OF THE SPIRITS TEACHING, WITHOUT HVMANE-LEARNING: OR A TREATISE, TENDING TO PROUE <hi>HV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANE-LEARNING</hi> TO BE NO HELP TO the Spirituall underſtanding of the Word of GOD</p>
            <p>Written (if it may be) for the Silencing of ſuch falſe and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous reports, as have been rumored about concerning this Matter; and alſo for the affording of true information to all ſuch as deſire to know the Truth.</p>
            <p>By SAMUEL HOW.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 14.5.</bibl>
               <p>A Faithfull witneſse will not lye, but a falſe record will ſpeake lyes.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eſay. 57.14.</bibl>
               <p>Caſt ye up, caſt ye up, prepare the way, take up the ſtumbling blocke out of the way of my people.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mal. 2.1, 2.</bibl>
               <p>And now ô ye Prieſts, this Commandement is for you, if ye will not heare it, nor conſider it in your heart, to give glory to my name, (ſaith the Lord of hoſts) I will even ſend a curſe upon you, and will curſe your bleſſings, yea I have curſed them already, becauſe ye do not conſider it in your heart.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 11.25.26.</bibl>
               <p>At that time Ieſus anſwered and ſaid, I thanke thee ô Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord of heaven and earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and men of underſtanding, and haſt revealed them unto babes, even ſo Father becauſe thy good pleaſure was ſuch.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luk. 16.15.</bibl>
               <p>Then he ſaid unto them, ye are they that juſtify your ſelves before men, but God knowes your hearts, for that which is highly eſteemed among men is abomination in the ſight of God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 11.6.</bibl>
               <p>And Bleſſed is he that shall not be offended in me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>See alſo</hi> Eſay. 29.14. <hi>and</hi> Rev. 2.24.25.</p>
            <p>Seen, Allowed, and Printed, by us <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL SVCH AS LOVE THE TRUTH IN <hi>SINSERITY,</hi> LIGHT AND UNDERSTANDING BE MULTIPLYED THROUGH JESUS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ODS</hi> Gracious Promiſe it is (Chriſtian Reader) <hi>that by the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>breath of his mouth, and the brighneſſe of his comming he will reveale the Man of Sin, and Sonne of Perdition:</hi> Yet thus witneſſeth the Spirit, that when it shall ſo come to paſſe, <hi>that the Viall of Gods wrath ſhall be</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reve.</hi> 16.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>powred upon the Throne of the Beaſt,</hi> to the darkening of his Kingdome, and diſcovering of thoſe ſtrong Deluſions, whereby he hath long deluded the world, that then the men of that throne <hi>ſhall gnaw their tongues for ſorrow, and ſhall blaſpheme the God of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which to me appeares to be fulfilled and made good concerning this following Treatiſe: <hi>1. that when as the Lord by his Word the breath of his mouth hath blown out ſome ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit, which I conceive to be</hi> Humane-Learning, <hi>which is ſo much magnified, as being a helpe, whereby to underſtand the mind of</hi> God.</p>
            <p>This matter hath ſo vexed and tormented the men of that Throne, that even He himſelfe, at whoſe requeſt I was moved to open this portion of Scripture, <hi>2 Pet. 3.16.</hi> hath (as I am credibly informed) reported about this City, that I made a Calfe (meaning a falſe and unſound expoſition) and when I had done danced about it; herein expoſing not onely me, but the very Truth it ſelfe, which I in this point
<pb facs="tcp:4451:3"/>delivered, to the deriſion, and contempt, and Table-talke, of ſuch, as bad rather be deceived and beleeve their Learned Teachers (as men call them) on their bare word (having the Faith of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Lord of Glory with reſpect of Perſons) then to receive and juſtifie the Truth of <hi>God,</hi> if the Meſſenger be weake and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his meſſage in power, much plaineſſe, and demonſtration of the ſpirit. And not beautified with the excellency of ſpeech, and ſwelling words of mans wiſdome, which is <hi>enmity to God.</hi> It croſſeth and oppoſeth the ſimplicity of his way in the <hi>diſpenſation of the Glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Goſpell.</hi> And therfore <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid of it, as <hi>Symon Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Symon Magus,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8, 21 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet (me thinks) <hi>ſuch men,</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ</hi> 5.4.</note> as would carry the <hi>ſhew of Godlineſſe,</hi> should remember the Councel of the Apoſtle, <hi>that ſuch Carriages are things not ſeemly;</hi> though for my owne part, I bleſse the <hi>Lord</hi> for it, being to me a more ſtrong confirmation, that I have the Truth on my ſide: For thus was<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord</hi> ſerved by the Wiſe and Learned <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when as he taught them ſuch a Doctrine as pleaſed them not: And thus was <hi>Paul</hi> the Preacher of Righteouſneſſe dealt by of the leareed<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Athenians,</hi> even for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Reſurrection. Likewiſe I read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Heb. 11.</hi> that this in former times was part of the tryall, that the <hi>Lord</hi> exerciſed his Witneſſes withall, even <hi>mockings, verſ. 36.</hi> And therfore as our Saviour teacheth me, I have in this caſe great cauſe to be <hi>glad</hi> and <hi>rejoyce,</hi> for they having ſo ſerved <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> my <hi>Lord,</hi> and his faithfull followers; then what am I, that I should be one of that number, that have ſo large<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>incouragement</hi> and <hi>reward promiſed:</hi> I shall therfore quietly paſſe by all ſuch things, and onely<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.3</note> with <hi>Job</hi> in his diſtreſſed condition, crave that he and all you that have done this thing will <hi>ſuffer me to ſpeake, and when I have ſpoken mock on;</hi> ſeeing as the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.2.</note> Servant of <hi>God</hi> ſaid, <hi>Indeed, becauſe ye are the people onely, Wiſdome muſt dye with you;</hi> ſo will I make bold to ſay to you alſo: Yet for all his <hi>underſtanding</hi> and ſuch others as heard me, they fayled of their <hi>zeale</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>glory,</hi> in that they ſought not to ſuppreſſe and throw down that Calfe of <hi>diſhonour,</hi> which muſt needs (being an Idol) be a very high provocation in the eyes of his Glory; which he that put me upon this Exerciſe having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt it, when it was finisht, and with much paſſion manifeſted his great diſlike thereof before many witneſſes, ought eſpecially, and was obliged to have done, being then lovingly requeſted by a friend that was there preſent, for the ſatisfaction of all that Aſſembly to Inſtance (if not in all) yet at leaſt in ſome particular Scripture wherein I had
<pb facs="tcp:4451:3"/>perverted it, ſeeing he had openly caſt an Aſpertion on all that I had ſaid; but neither he, nor any of his Profeſſion, though many were then preſent, did undertake this taske, nor yet to this day, hath He, or any of them endeavoured it. So it may appeare my Errour was not ſo great, or none at all, that they could prove; or elſe their <hi>zeale</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his Truth, and their <hi>Charity</hi> to Me and othes very ſmall. And if there were a Calfe, It was their <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi> which the men of this <hi>Throne</hi> ſet up, and themſelves danced about it, whileſt I to their great <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>diſcontent</hi> was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring with all the power and might that <hi>God</hi> aſſiſted me with, utterly to caſt down, grind it to powder, and to blow it away with the <hi>word of God, with the breath of his mouth:</hi> Whether it be thus, or no, I commend now to the judgement of all ſuch as love and know the <hi>truth;</hi> not doubting but there will be ſome found, that out of love will reprove what is amiſse, and ſo <hi>turne the ſinner out of the errour of his way,</hi> though ſome others, as<note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>forge lyes</hi> (as I could name divers) <hi>who are Phyſitians of no value.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>God who knows the hearts of all men,</hi> knows that it was not my intent at all at that time to have medled in this Argument, nor with this Scripture, not till the night before I ſpake of it, and all becauſe I knew if I did, it would be offenſive, as it hath proved; and and what I did herein it was by the advice of Friends. But now I ſee that <hi>Gods</hi> hand was in it, and I doubt not but for good: though it is, and may be my portion deeply to ſuffer for it: and for men to be offended at the <hi>truth,</hi> and ſuch as declare it, is no new thing, even for the<note n="‡" place="margin">Pſa. 118.22. Act. 4.11. Iſay. 8.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>builders</hi> themſelves to ſtumble at the ſtumbling ſtone: <hi>But leaving all ſuch to ſtand or fall to their own Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Somthing remaines to be ſpoken concerning the matter following, for the preventing of ſuch things as may further be objected againſt it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Though the matter be the ſame in ſubſtance that it was at the firſt delivery, yet ſomwhat may be wanting, and is, which was then ſaid; and more is added in other reſpects then at that time was ſpoken, which I thought fit to give notice of.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Another exception and that of great moment, is, that I have bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſphemed againſt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in ſaying, that He was without <hi>Humane-Learning.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now beſides what is anſwered hereunto in the firſt Objection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the firſt Doctrine; if any yet remain unſatisfied, and will affirme the contrary, <hi>Let them declare,</hi> (as the<note n="‡" place="margin">Rom. 11.34.35.</note> Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>who was his Councellour, and who taught him, and he ſhall be recompenced:</hi> The Scripture tells us, <hi>that He grew in Wiſdome and Stature,</hi> and ſo couples them alike together: Now none will affirme
<pb facs="tcp:4451:4"/>that He Learned his <hi>Stature:</hi> then from the like will I affirme, that He Learned not His <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> no more then He did His <hi>Stature;</hi> and ſo if none taught him, then muſt it needs follow that He was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Humane-Learning,</hi> for we in common ſpeech call them <hi>unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> which were never taught, as did the<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 7.15. Acts 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Jewes;</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> preſuppoſeth one to Teach, ſo that me thinks) it is but requiſite, if any do ſo affirme, that they should declare his Teacher, which if they cannot doe, why then should they affirme Him to have <hi>Humane-Learning.</hi> And me thinks, the matter being rightly conſidered, it will be found <hi>blaſphemy</hi> for any to affirme that He had <hi>Humane-Learning,</hi> ſeeing that in ſo doing, they call in queſtion the perfection of His <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> as if there were others that could adde unto Him, ſeeing all grant that the Maſter is above the Scholler: and the Scripture witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for me, <hi>that at</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Luke 2.46, 47.</note> 
               <hi>12 yeares old,</hi> ſuch was His <hi>Wiſdome</hi> obſerved amonſt <hi>the Doctors,</hi> as that they were <hi>aſtoniſhed at his underſtanding and anſwers;</hi> and doubtleſſe this was a part of their great <hi>wonder,</hi> ſeeing that He never Learned, as it was the <hi>Councels wonder alſo concerning</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Acts 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Peter and John.</hi> Therfore for any to affirme Him to be by men taught, is to take that glory from Him which He had of His own, and ſo they are moſt like to be them that <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> It is alſo very likely that <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>vain-glory</hi> wilbe imputed to me, as it hath been already, that I being as I am, should undertake to maintaine that which all godly and learned men are contrary to me in.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwere, that it is no ſtrange thing for the Servants of <hi>God</hi> to meet with ſuch hard meaſure, even for declaring of the <hi>truth;</hi> for <hi>ſo was Joſeph</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">Gen. 37.8.10, 11.</note> dealt by even of his <hi>Father and Brethren:</hi> and ſo was<note n="†" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> uſed for ſpeaking <hi>for the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> you shall find was<note n="‡̶" place="margin">Act. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſcoffed at by the learned Athenians:</hi> And ſeeing that it hath alwayes bin ſo with <hi>Gods</hi> Servants, why should not I affirme with the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.</note> Apoſtle, <hi>not to paſſe to be judged of men,</hi> whatſoever they be, though godly, wiſe, learned; ſeeing that as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>it makes no matter to me, God is no</hi>
               <note n="‡̶" place="margin">Gal. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>accepter of perſons:</hi> And therfore I hold it a defence ſufficient with <hi>David</hi> to ſay,<note n="‡" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.29.</note> 
               <hi>Is there not a Cauſe? ſeeing that there is none that I know of that will ſtand up for the Lord, againſt thoſe that defie the hoſt of Iſrael, becauſe that they be not Goliah-like, Men of ſtature, having Boots of braſſe, and ſuch like furniture, as that the fleſhly hearts of men dare not looke ſuch in the face; and all becauſe that they bee ſo ſtrongly furniſhed with Mans ſtrength:</hi> Though that the Souldiers of the <hi>Lord of hoſts,</hi> may
<pb facs="tcp:4451:4"/>with one blaſt of a <hi>Rammes horne,</hi> through the might of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joſh. 6.20.</note> blow down the ſtrong Wall of this ſpirituall <hi>Jericho:</hi> ſeeing that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>that by the</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Mat. 21.16.</note> 
               <hi>mouth of babes and ſucklings he will perfit his praiſe,</hi> and this if Babes should neglect to doe, <hi>the ſtones would cry,</hi> whence is to be obſerved our Saviour deſcends from Babes to Stones, and not from Babes to Learned men, for he hath Choſen ſuch to bring forth His <hi>Righteouſneſſe as the light;</hi> for He himſelfe doth not <hi>deſpiſe the day of</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Zach. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſmall things.</hi> Now theſe things conſidered, why should any with the proud<note n="§" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>Phariſees</hi> diſdaine at what the <hi>Lord</hi> will doe; but lay their hands upon their mouthes and ſay nothing becauſe He<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> 
               <hi>doth it;</hi> And ſeeing it is <hi>the Lords</hi>
               <note n="‡̶" place="margin">Pſal. 118.23.</note> 
               <hi>doing, why ſhould it not be Merveylous in our eyes:</hi> Though I doubt not but the <hi>Lord</hi> will in his good time bring forth one <hi>learned Moſes,</hi> and another as excellent that wayes as was <hi>Paul,</hi> and cauſe them diſclayming that Humane excellencie to magnifie the foolishneſſe of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.25.</note> to be wiſer then the wiſdome of men, and ſo every way convince men of their folly this way to his prayſe.</p>
            <p>And in the meane while let them that can receive this for Truth, receive it, and let none be ſo conceited of Learned-men, <hi>as if the word of God came onely to them, and from them, as</hi> Paul ſaid to<note n="‡" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.36, 37.</note> ſome that were puffed up. But let ſuch as are ſpirituall know that the <hi>Lord</hi> reveales his Myſteries to whom he pleaſeth, and where he will; and therfore <hi>the eye of none ſhould be evill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is good,</hi> but we should learne, as the Wiſeman ſaith, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.11</note> 
               <hi>the race is not alway to the ſwift, nor the battell to the ſtrong:</hi> but it may ſo prove<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that little <hi>David</hi> without <hi>Sauls</hi> Armour onely with a Sling and a Stone through the Name of the <hi>Lord,</hi> may ſo wound great <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> the enemy of <hi>God</hi> and his people, as that he may receive his deadly wound, and ly groveling on the ground, to the diſmayment of all the Hoſt of the <hi>Phyliſtims,</hi> and great rejoycing of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and this the Stone that is hewen out of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine without hands, is onely able to doe. Therfore let all that feare the <hi>Lord</hi> take heed that they leane not to their own Wiſdome, but ſo much the more that any of us have Wiſdome, and Vnderſtanding, Memory, and ſuch like naturall parts, above other, ſo much the more let us be watchfull and carefull over our ſelves, as knowing that the<note n="§" place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh is enmity againſt God,</hi> and is ready to but againſt the Spirit: and now to draw to a Concluſion of all in the words of the Prophet,<note n="†" place="margin">Iſay 44.25.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord fruſtrateth the tokens of the lyars, and maketh the Diviners madde, turneth wiſe-men backward, and maketh their Knowledge fooliſhneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:5"/>
            <p>If any shall except againſt the matter, for the rudeneſſe of it, as that it is without forme, or Learning, all ſuch are to know that it is but ſutable to the whole argument, and that if it should be otherwiſe, I should condemn that in practiſe which I juſtifie in words, and ſo make my ſelfe a treſpaſser. Thus I commit this my labour, with all thoſe that out of love to the Truth shall ſeek information in this matter, to the bleſſing of the moſt High, and remaine an unfeigned welwiller of all them that love the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in <hi>ſincerity.</hi> The <hi>25</hi> day of the Firſt Moneth, <hi>1639.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SAMUEL HOW</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:5"/>
            <head>THE SVFFICIENCIE OF THE SPIRITS TEACHING, WITHOUT HVMAN-LEARNING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>The text, 2 PETER 3.16.</bibl>
                  <p>As one that in all his Epiſtles ſpeakes of theſe things, in which are ſome things hard to be underſtood: which they that are Vnlearned and Vnſtable, wreſt, as they doe alſo the other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures unto their own deſtruction.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE Words, that I am alotted to ſpeake from at this time, have reſpect, as it ſhould ſeeme, to ſuch things as the Apoſtle had ſpoken of Before, which things ſeeme to me to be thoſe that are contained from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnning of the ſecond Chapter to the end of the thirteenth verſe of this third Chapter; and the foureteenth verſe containes <hi>Peters</hi> exhortation, ſtrengthened in the fifteenth verſe, by his Brother <hi>Pauls</hi> writings, who in all his Epiſtles ſpeaks of theſe things, as of the <hi>comming of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> and other things, ſuch as are herein contained; among the which (that is) <hi>Pauls</hi> writings in his Epiſtles, ſome things were hard to be <hi>underſtood,</hi> and ſo indeed was the <hi>comming of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:6"/>which it ſhould ſeem was hard of them to be <hi>underſtood,</hi> and that appeares by his earneſt writing to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Theſ. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</hi> at the beginning.</note> 
               <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> where he exorts them <hi>that they should not ſuddenly be moved, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Word, nor Epiſtle, as it were from him, as if the day of Chriſt were at hand, for there were many things to be fulfilled firſt, as a departure from the Faith,</hi> the riſing up, the perfection and the conſumption of the <hi>Man of ſinne:</hi> and this it ſhould ſeeme though he had told them of it before, yet to them it was hard to be underſtood, which had the true Learning here meant, which things they that were Unlearned and Unſtable, perverted as they did other Scriptures to their own <hi>deſtruction.</hi> Therfore the great thing here to be minded, is to find out what this <hi>learning</hi> is that <hi>Peter</hi> here intends. And, Secondly, who they be that are the <hi>unlearned ones:</hi> and by that we ſhall eaſily find who they be that are the <hi>perverters</hi> of the Scriptures to their owne <hi>deſtruction.</hi> For this end therfore I will conſider what this <hi>learning is not,</hi> and then what <hi>it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What Learning it is not.</note> 
               <hi>It is not Humane-Learning.</hi> That I may not be miſconceived about it, I will here lay down my underſtanding in it; and by <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> I doe not mind the knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of our own <hi>language,</hi> which every man of what tongue ſoever he be, might in ſome meaſure be taught of another, as the Parents teach their Children, and they learne of them: of this there is a naturall neceſſity, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>How shall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.</note> now the hearing there mentioned muſt needs be a naturall hearing, ſeeing it is ſet before Faith; and this hearing muſt needs be the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the ſound of words ſpoken. Now thus <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> and all the reſt <hi>learned</hi> the fooliſh things ſpoken of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.: and thus I acknowledg that there is none but in ſome meaſure have this <hi>learning,</hi> and muſt of neceſſity have it, to underſtand <hi>Gods</hi> mind in an ordinary way. But by <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> all along in this matter, which I oppoſe, It is the knowledge of Arts and Sciences, divers Tongues, and much reading, and a perſiſting in theſe things, ſoe as there-by to be made able to underſtand the <hi>mind</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in his Word; this is it that I condemn from the word of Truth, for being that by which any is made able ſpiritually to underſtand the <hi>mind</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which the Apoſte ſaith, cannot be attained to by <hi>the words which mans wiſdome teacheth:</hi> all which, theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies are ſaid to be.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13.</note> So that by <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> I doe here underſtand, that, whereby certain men doe excell, and are farre
<pb facs="tcp:4451:6"/>above and beyond other ordinary men; and in this ſenſe doe I underſtand that the Councel Judged <hi>Peter and Iohn to be no ſuch learned men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13.</note> For we in common ſpeech doe oppoſe a learned man to one that otherwiſe can read and write in his own tongue, though he doe not underſtand the grounds of his own ſpeech, as the other man that is learned doth, as may appeare by the Booke called the <hi>English School-maſter.</hi> And ſo ſuch <hi>learning</hi> doe I not conceive to be here meant, which I conclude for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe that then <hi>Peter</hi> muſt of neceſſity condemn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Reaſon.</note> for he was a Man that in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 4 13.</note> Councels knowledge was ſuch an <hi>unlearned man,</hi> and ſo muſt needs himſelfe lye under that blame that he laves upon others, therfore <hi>Humane-Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is not here that which he intends.</item>
               <item>2. Becauſe <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> is a<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>rudiment</hi> of this world;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Reaſon.</note> hence is it that our Saviour acknowledgeth that his Myſteries <hi>were hid from the</hi>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Learned:</hi> but they were not hid from his Diſciples, <hi>for unto them it was</hi>
                  <note n="§" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdome. And the rudiments of this world are not after Chriſt,</hi> the Apoſtle tells us: therfore <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> cannot be it that <hi>Peter</hi> here minds.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Becauſe the naturall man cannot</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>perceive the things of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> Reaſon.</note> but a meere naturall man, may be a great worldly Learned man, as were the Aegyptians, and Babylonians, and as are many of the Romiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites; therfore for this cauſe, that is not the <hi>learning</hi> here meant.</item>
               <item>4. Becauſe ſuch of <hi>Gods</hi> ſervants, as have had ſuch kind of <hi>learning,</hi> when as they came to know <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they forſook it all,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Reaſon.</note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> when he came to age, <hi>though he was</hi>
                  <note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.22.</note> 
                  <hi>learned in all the wiſdome of the Aegyptians, yet by Faith he forſooke all the treaſures of Aegypt,</hi> and this being one of <hi>Aegypts treaſures,</hi> he forſooke this alſo, for when he ſaith <hi>treaſures,</hi> there none is excepted: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in aſmuch as <hi>learning</hi> was one, aſwell as <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>honours,</hi> he forſook that alſo, as ſeeing by Faith a better <hi>treaſure</hi> in the worſt condition among the people of <hi>God,</hi> then in the beſt condition in the world, ſuppoſe it be <hi>learning.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The like is to be ſeen in <hi>Paul, who counted all things loſſe and dung</hi> that he <hi>might winne Chriſt,</hi> even the <hi>righteouſneſſe of the Law it ſelfe,</hi> which is farre beyond all this, and all this he did that he might know him: Wherein the Apoſtle gives me to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that all ſuch things were but hinderances to keep him from the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt</hi> to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> which is it that
<pb facs="tcp:4451:7"/>here I mind alſo: therfore likewiſe this is not the <hi>learning</hi> here meant, ſeeing it was rejected of them, therfore it was no help nor furtherance to them to know <hi>Chriſt</hi> by; but lets and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances, and ſo much appeares by thoſe converts in <hi>Acts</hi> 19.18, 19. <hi>Who when they beleeved are ſaid, ſuch of them as uſed curious Arts, to burn their Books,</hi> declaring that now they had met with <hi>learning</hi> of farre greater worth, then their curious Arts, and therfore now they burn their Books, declaring that now they had no more need of them, and ſo I conclude that ſuch as this is not the <hi>learning</hi> here meant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What Learning it is.</note>
               <hi>I now come to manifeſt what Learning it is the Apoſtle here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>learning</hi> here intended by the Apoſtle, it is as I underſtand, That <hi>ſound knowledge,</hi> and <hi>ſure information</hi> that every Chriſtian hath in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7.</note> whereby he is ſo deeply rooted, and ſo ſurely grafted into him by Faith, as that he abides un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveably ſetled in him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.17.18.</note> as therby he abides ſtable in the ſure <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo much here me thinks the Apoſtle gives us to underſtand,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6.</note> how that the <hi>unlearned,</hi> they be <hi>unſtable:</hi> then on the contrary, the <hi>learned</hi> they are ſtable, beleeving, and being layd on the true Foundation, they ſhall never be confounded, or aſhamed. Now ſuch as theſe are, that are <hi>learned</hi> as <hi>the truth is in Ieſus,</hi> theſe may well ſay to the greateſt worldly <hi>learned</hi> ones, as <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to the Eunuch, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt:</hi> and not onely ſo, but ſuch may teach them the underſtanding of the myſtery, ſaying, theſe are taught and inſtructed by the teachings of the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> agreeable to theſe Scriptures: <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>That it hath not entred into the heart of man to conceive of that which God by his Spirit</hi> (which ſearcheth the deep things of <hi>God</hi>) <hi>hath reavealed unto us.</hi> And this the Apoſtle further explaines, <hi>that as no man knows the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of a man which is in him: ſo the things of God knows no man, no not</hi> a worldly learned man, <hi>but by the Spirit of God:</hi> and ſo he goes on to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the ſpirit of the world, from <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> and ſhewes, that, that is it, wherby the things of <hi>God</hi> are known, and alſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to others: ſo that all the things of <hi>God</hi> both for matter and manner flow from the wiſdome of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> and not what mans wiſdome teacheth, which is to compare ſpirituall things and carnall things together, as <hi>tongues,</hi> and <hi>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and ſuch like: but <hi>Gods Spirit teacheth us to compare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things,</hi> and ſo he goes on and declares that onely
<pb facs="tcp:4451:7"/>ſuch that are taught by the Spirit, are capable of true diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſpiritual things, without being juſtly condemned of any, as truly having the mind of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> rightly and truly knowing the things that are of <hi>God,</hi> and with this agrees the witnes of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.26.27.</note> ſaying, <hi>theſe things have I written unto you concerning them that deceive you,</hi> wherby it appeares they had <hi>deceivers</hi> about them, and thoſe things were written concerning ſuch; But ſaith the Apoſtle in oppoſition to their <hi>deceivings,</hi> ye have received the <hi>Anoynting</hi> of him that dwells in you; and this <hi>anoynting</hi> that they had received doth he oppoſe to their <hi>deceiving,</hi> as being able throughly to teach them ſo, <hi>as that they needed not that any man teach them, ſave as that anoynting taught them:</hi> then ſeeing that that <hi>anoynting</hi> never did teach them ſuch <hi>tongues</hi> or <hi>arts,</hi> as were <hi>humane,</hi> therfore the Saints by the Apoſtles grant had not need of any ſuch <hi>learning,</hi> and yet this <hi>anoynting</hi> taught all <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> in it alſo. And yet further our<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.7. <hi>with</hi> 13.</note> Saviour <hi>himſelfe concludes this point, shewing that when he hath ſent the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, the Spirit of Truth to them, that then he shall leade them into all truth:</hi> whence I doe conclude, that for the Diſciples know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>truth</hi> there, was no more neceſſary according to the <hi>mind</hi> of him that was <hi>Truth,</hi> but the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to lead them into all <hi>truth</hi> without all errour, teaching by no <hi>humane meanes:</hi> the Reaſon why is rendered, <hi>becauſe it is ſufficient,</hi> and that is becauſe it ſpeakes from the Father, agreeable to that of our Saviour taken from the Prophet, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.45.</note> 
               <hi>we shall be all taught of God, and ſo indeed being taught of the Spirit, we are taught of the Ftther, and the Sonne alſo,</hi> which are all one; and ſo our <hi>learning</hi> comes to us, being taught of the Father, Sonne, and Spirit, for all our Inſtructers and Councellers, and this is all the <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> that we need, to know the things that are of <hi>God</hi> by, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his will: ſo from theſe words thus interpreted, the Concluſion comes to this,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Propoſition. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That ſuch as are taught by the Spirit of God, deſtitute of Humane-Learning, are the Learned ones that truly underſtand the Scriptures according to</hi> Peters <hi>mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, ſuch as are taught by the Spirit, without <hi>Humane-Learning,</hi> are ſuch perſons as rightly underſtand the Word: And this (me thinks) the whole Councel of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as wicked as they were, did in effect conclude,<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13.14.</note> conſidering <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> though <hi>unlearned men,</hi> yet they knew they had been with <hi>Ieſus</hi> by their boldneſſe, and ſo they had nothing to
<pb facs="tcp:4451:8"/>ſay againſt it: and yet though men ſhould oppoſe it, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.21.24.</note> Juſtifies it, with great thankfullneſſe to his Father, <hi>that having hid theſe s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings from the wiſe and prudent, he had revealed them to babes:</hi> Now that revealing muſt needs be by the Spirit, according to that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. And on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is it that our <hi>Lord</hi> comfort, his Diſciples telling them that <hi>all things were given him of his Father to reveale,</hi> and ſo in that regard he tells them that <hi>bleſſed are the eyes that ſee that, that they ſaw,</hi> which was as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God manifeſted in the flesh, which many wiſe men and Kings deſired to ſee, but could not ſee it,</hi> and ſo that was now made manifeſt to them, which before was hid from Wiſe-men and Scribes, and ſo was at the preſent alſo: for few of the Wiſe could attaine to the knowledge of Him and his Doctrine, as they did Now with this alſo agrees what our<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.23.29.</note> Saviour further affirmes to the Sadducse, who by reaſon of their Wiſdome and Learning thought to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled him, he tells them <hi>that they erred not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> for all their great Learning being deſtitute of <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit. Now by theſe Scriptures this poynt being thus confirmed, good Reaſon alſo may by <hi>Gods</hi> word be brought for the futher juſtifying of it, as</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe it is the good pleaſure of <hi>God</hi> to place our <hi>ſalvation</hi> in great contempt and enmity to mans <hi>wiſdome:</hi> hence is it that the Apoſtle ſaith, that he <hi>preached Chriſt crucified to the Iewes a</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſtumbling blocke, and to the Gretians foolishneſſe,</hi> for the Jewes we read in great contempt refuſed him, as <hi>Pilate</hi> bid them behold their<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.19.21.</note> King; preſently they cry <hi>away with him, away with him, Crucifie him:</hi> and ſo when <hi>Pilate</hi> had wrote on the Croſſe, that he was King of the Jewes, they tooke it as a great prejudice to them, and therfore wiſhed him to write, <hi>that he ſaid he was the King of the Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo as <hi>Peter</hi> tells them in <hi>Acts</hi> 3. <hi>they denyed him, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a murtherer to be given them,</hi> and to this agreed the Gentiles, for they had their hands alſo in his <hi>death:</hi> and we find that whenas <hi>Paul</hi> preached him at <hi>Athens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.18.23.</note> that then this ſaying of the Apoſtle here is made good both of Jewes and Gentiles: and indeed they both agree to hang him, betwixt heaven and earth, as being in their eſteem worthy of neither, and yet even in this Crucified <hi>Ieſus</hi> lyes contained the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note> all (both Jewes and Gentiles) that are ſaved: and in this deſpiſed <hi>Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> are all to rejoyce with the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6.14.</note> Apoſtle, to <hi>ſalvation:</hi> for in him thus diſhonourable and unmeet in mans wiſdome, <hi>lye hid all
<pb facs="tcp:4451:8"/>our heavenly</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>treaſures of wiſdome, righteouſneſse, ſanctification and redemption: for he is the wiſdome of God, and power of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.24.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon why ſuch as have <hi>Gods</hi> Spirit deſtitute of <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> come thus to know <hi>Gods mind,</hi> is,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> that (as the<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.29.</note> Apoſtle declares) <hi>no flesh should rejoyce in Gods preſence:</hi> now this <hi>learning</hi> is but fleſhly and carnall. Now the Apoſtles ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe is, though we had known<note n="‡" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> after the fleſh; yet now comming to be after <hi>God,</hi> we ſhould henceforth know him ſo no more: and here is a ſufficient Reaſon, becauſe <hi>knw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> is ſubject to puffe us up, as ſaith the<note n="§" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8.</note> Apoſtle: Whenas <hi>love,</hi> and the Learning of the Spirit, keeps us low in our own eyes, and cauſeth, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, our minds to be good, making us ſutable to the Apoſtles exhortations,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16.</note> ſaying, <hi>Be not high minded, but make your ſelves equall to them of the lower ſort;</hi> be not wiſe in your ſelves, but<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>let every man eſteem others better then himſelfe:</hi> and <hi>if any glory, let him</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31.</note> 
               <hi>glory in the Lord.</hi> Now he that hath theſe things, as <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> and Wiſdome more then another, let him weigh and conſider duly with himſelfe, whether he doth not think and conclude that he in regard of theſe things is not more to be reſpected then they that are without them: now then<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6.</note> this rejoycing is not good, for it is a rejoycing in the fleſh, and ſutable to<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>works,</hi> and ſo not of <hi>God:</hi> and yet ſo is it that for our hearts we cannot but think better of our ſelves for theſe things, then of others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, &amp; ſo we may ſee the Apoſtles words fulfild, that the <hi>wiſdome of the</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>flesh,</hi> that is, whatſoever the fleſh is excellent in, it is <hi>enmity to God,</hi> it is not ſubject to the Law of <hi>God,</hi> neither indeed can be.</p>
            <p>Anotder Cauſe, why the <hi>Spirits teaching</hi> is <hi>ſufficient without Humane-Learning,</hi> is, becauſe, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in him,</hi> that is, perfect and full in him: and this he ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens yet further from this conſideration, that he is the head of all Principalities and Powers, ſo that if there were any thing elſe, to make us compleat, he being the Head of all, we ſhould have it: but he hath given nothing but his<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit to profit withall,</hi> therfore we are compleat by it alone; and therfore is it that <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20.21.</note> exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to keep that which was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, which was the Faith taught by the Word and Spirit, and wiſheth him to avoyd and beware of Science, that is, all knowledge naturall, which is comprehended under <note n=",," place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8</note> 
               <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> learned, prophane and vaine bablings, and oppoſitions
<pb facs="tcp:4451:9"/>to the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo much is by the Apoſtle there declared, ſaying, <hi>which while ſome have luſted after, they have erred from the Faith:</hi> ſo that it is moſt plain and cleare, that theſe things are ſo farre from perfecting men, or helping of them in the knowledge of the <hi>truth,</hi> as that they hinder and cauſe ſuch as profeſſe them to erre from the Faith: even all the ſeaven Liberall Sciences, for all be but Science, and all this Science or knowledge is falſly ſayd to be of uſe in the Goſpell; Profane and vaine bablings are farre better names for them, and oppoſitions, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> teaching, and he ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>I thinke I have the Spirit of God,</hi> and ſo indeed he had without doubt, and ſo our ground remaines good, <hi>that we are compleat in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another conſideration confirming this Concluſion,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> is from the Apoſtles<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note> adviſe, <hi>let no man deceive himſelfe,</hi> and that in the true way of attaining <hi>wiſdome;</hi> he declares what it is in theſe words, <hi>that ſuch a one is to become a foole that he may be wiſe,</hi> and how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that, but by knowing that indeed there is nothing in all mans wiſdome to be any whit helpfull but hurtfull to him in attaining and comprehending the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Now what is more fooliſh to a man then to know that there is nothing that all the wits of man can reach unto, that can benefit him: and if nothing, then not this thing in queſtion, but that it muſt needs be that we muſt be fooles to it, and what is the true marke of a foole but to be ignorant, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge, therfore we call them fooles in the world, and ſo is it here; the beſt way for a man not to deceive himſelfe, is to know nothing of this <hi>learning,</hi> nor any other fleſhly excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie that ſo he may learn true <hi>wiſdome:</hi> and the Apoſtle doth (me thinks, ſufficiently confirme this advice of his, againſt all exceptions, <hi>the Lord knows</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the thoughts of men be</hi> vaine: Men think highly of their own conceits this way, yet if no man will take this his councell for <hi>wiſdome</hi> in this kind, yet the <hi>Lord</hi> concludes the <hi>truth</hi> of it, and he knows the <hi>thoughts</hi> of men to be vaine, that think <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> ſome helpe: but let them think what they will, the <hi>Lord</hi> is againſt them in it, for he knows that it is ſure that they are deceived, <hi>for his thoughts be not as mans thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now another Cauſe that confirmes me in this Concluſion, is becauſe that whereſoever the Apoſtle honours the <hi>Spirits teaching,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> and preferres it, uſually he at the ſame time caſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon this <hi>learning,</hi> as is to be ſeen in many places<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:9"/>(ſaith he) <hi>ſent me to preach the Goſpell, not with the wiſdome of words, leaſt I should make the croſſe of Chriſt, or the Goſpel of Chriſt of none effect,</hi> where we ſee, that for good reaſon he rejects the very wiſdome of words in preaching of the Goſpel, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, leaſt if he ſhould have done otherwiſe, he ſhould have made it of no effect, becauſe he was to declare the <hi>ſincere word,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt mingling; as if he ſhould ſay, ſuch manner of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaching is a fooliſh preaching, but it is ſo onely <hi>to them that perish; but to ſuch as are ſaved it is the power of God,</hi> without what man expects: and therfore he<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.3</note> ſaith againe, <hi>he was jealous over them with a godly jealouſie,</hi> for he had prepared them a pure Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>I feare that as the Serpent beguiled Eve,</hi> but how? <hi>through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds should be corrupt,</hi> that is, putrified, and infected from the <hi>ſincerity</hi> that is in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> This we ſee was <hi>Pauls</hi> feare, that while he was abſent their minds ſhould be withdrawn from the fooliſhneſſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the ſimplicity, ſincerity, and truth thereof, and this they ſhould be withdrawn from by the ſubtilty of Satan that old Serpent, in his inſtruments the falſe teachers; this he feares becauſe of their fleſhlyneſſe that was in them, which was ready to yeeld to their wiles by reaſon of their ſubtilty that way, for by faire words and flatteries they deceived the<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>hearts</hi> of the ſimple, and with this their craftineſſe they lye in wait to<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.14.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; thus contemptuouſly doth <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeake of theſe things, in oppoſition to the true <hi>learning,</hi> as is further to be ſeen in many places, of which I will name one more, and that from the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle chap. 1. verſe 16. <hi>For we ſaith he followed not deceiveable Fables, when we opened unto you the power and comming of our Lord Ieſus.</hi> Now ſuch names as theſe are, doth the Apoſtle chooſe to caſt on mans excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as in divers other<note n="§" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. <hi>and</hi> 4.7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.9.</note> places which declare what contempt is caſt on ſuch learning in oppoſition to the Spirit of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now one thing more which I conceive obſervable for the proofe of this point in hand,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Reaſon,</hi>
               </note> is drawn from the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>The Spirit ſearches the deep things of God,</hi> and 14. <hi>The ſpirituall man diſcernes all things;</hi> if then the Spirit ſearcheth the deep things of <hi>God,</hi> and that diſcernes all things, what need we more: and with this agrees the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.27.</note> ſaying, <hi>And ye need not that any man teach you, ſave as that Anoynting teacheth you.</hi> Then I conclude, <hi>That we need not that any man teach us, not the Maſter, nor any of his followers, for the Diſciples of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>doe learne (as the truth is) in him, and of him, and they have received the Spirit of</hi> God, <hi>that they might know the things of</hi> God: therfore we may
<pb facs="tcp:4451:10"/>well be without any mans <hi>learning,</hi> and have no need of it; and ſo the point is cleare and plain, <hi>That ſuch as are taught by Gods Spirit without that Learning, do truly underſtand the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I judge it neceſſary alſo to be underſtood of the Reader, what I doe underſtand by <hi>human wiſdome,</hi> as well as <hi>Human-Learning:</hi> by <hi>human wiſdome</hi> I doe underſtand whatſoever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares <hi>excellent</hi> in <hi>mans underſtanding,</hi> as he is left without <hi>Gods ſpirits teaching;</hi> this the more <hi>excellent</hi> it is to him that is <hi>carnall,</hi> ſo much the worſe it is: therfore it is ſaid of ſuch by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>that whenas they profeſſed themſelves to be wiſe, then they became fooles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note> And ſaith our Saviour, <hi>If the light which is in thee</hi> (which I mind to be meant of <hi>mens underſtanding</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi>) <hi>be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>how great is that darkneſſe:</hi> So that by <hi>mans wiſdome</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <hi>whatſoever ſeems excellent to him with which he would honour God withall, that he is not the Author of,</hi> as <hi>eloquence,</hi> and <hi>faire ſpeeches,</hi> and any thing in that way: ſuch as the Greeks ſought after, as men doe now adayes. This I do the rather differ from <hi>Haman-Learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22.</note> becauſe it ſeems to me that the <hi>Scripture</hi> differenceth them, <hi>Acts</hi> 22. and the difference rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood may prevent juſt exception, and give light to the right underſtanding of the whole matter: for this <hi>wiſdome</hi> is made by the Apoſtle, and that rightly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>to be enmity to the Spirit of God,</hi> and impoſſible to ſubmit to it, it is ſo contrary.</p>
            <p>Now followes to be anſwered ſuch Objections as are made againſt it, as firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> That of <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>That a Bishop muſt be no young Scholler, leſt he being puffed up fall into the condemnation of the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> The Scholerſhip <hi>Paul</hi> means here, <hi>is the teaching of the Spirit, whereby the man is made ſound in the Faith,</hi> for that <hi>learning</hi> onely will make men low in their own eyes, as is before declared, and he that is <hi>unſound</hi> in the <hi>faith,</hi> will ever be found the moſt <hi>lofty</hi> and puffed up in his own <hi>conceit,</hi> and ſo be rejected of <hi>God</hi> as the Devil was, though he was in heaven with <hi>God,</hi> yet being puffed up, he was rejected of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>caſt down to hell;</hi> to which example <hi>Paul</hi> here alludes, as I conceive, and that right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for a Biſhop in the Church is in reſpect of his <hi>ſpirituall ſtate</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> in <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>fellowship with God, and that in Heaven,</hi> as the whole Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> deſcribes the Church to be: Now ſuch as by the Church ſhould be choſen to that <hi>ſtate,</hi> being <hi>young Scholers,</hi> that is, <hi>not ſoundly taught in the truth by the Spirit,</hi> he is in great danger, the more other <hi>learning</hi> that he hath, ſo much the more to be <hi>puffed up.</hi> This I beleeve was
<pb facs="tcp:4451:10"/>the cauſe of <hi>Diotrephes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>pride,</hi> he wanted this Scholerſhip, and that cauſed him to ſeek the preheminence: And this, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our great Scholers think of themſelves, is the cauſe of the <hi>high conceits</hi> that they have of themſelves, and their <hi>knnow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> above others, that want their <hi>learning,</hi> even this, becauſe they be but young Scholers (if that) in the Schole of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and thene is it they are ſo puft up with the vain glory of their fleſhly <hi>learning,</hi> that they think that none that are not as themſelves are fit to be their fellowes, and ſo know not now <hi>that they be wretched, poore, miſerable, blind, and naked:</hi> though they conceive themſelves <hi>to be rich, and have need of nothing,</hi> as did the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> and ſo indeed are <hi>fallen into the condemnation of the Devil,</hi> as being rejected of <hi>God, for he reſiſts the proud,</hi> and ſuch as are puft up, <hi>and gives grace to the</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>humble, and ſuch as are low in their own eyes:</hi> Now whether theſe men <hi>Humanly learned,</hi> be they <hi>that are puft up</hi> or <hi>low in their own eyes,</hi> as <hi>meane as he that is unlearned,</hi> I leave to all that have eyes to ſee to looke into it, and ſo to judge whether they are not yet to learne <hi>Pauls</hi> Scholerſhip.</p>
            <p>Further I ſay it is here to be minded, that if it ſhould be <hi>Human-Lerning</hi> that is here meant, then <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould teach <hi>Timothy</hi> for to teach the Church to chuſe ſuch Scholers, as had more <hi>learning</hi> then had their Maſter <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> Now this ſome ſay is <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> and threaten me ſorely for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer them, that conſidering <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Divine nature, ſo he is God over all, and ſo gives all things,</hi> Acts 17.25. and ſo he is <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>giver of every good gift,</hi> and ſo <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> and <hi>wiſdome</hi> are<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.37.</note> 
               <hi>of him, and through him:</hi> and ſo much (but that men are maliciouſly bent) they might diſcerne, that I in this <hi>argument</hi> had not to deale with him, as <hi>God,</hi> but as the <hi>Miniſter of God, adminiſtring for the good of his body,</hi> according to that, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. where he ſaith, <hi>the ſpirit of the Lord hath Anoynted me, that I should Miniſter, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo in this <hi>argument</hi> he is by the Apoſtle ſet forth as a Man,<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth, a man approved of God;</hi> and as ſuch a man ſo admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring I doe-ſtill affirme, and that with great confidence, that He was <hi>unlearned</hi> in this conſideration, and without the <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> that we ſpeake of:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 50.4,</note> and ſo the <hi>tongue of the " Learned</hi> that" was ſaid to be given Him, is<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>interpreted</hi> by the ſame Prophet to be the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> for ſaith He, <hi>the Spirit of the Lord hath Anoynted me that I should preach;</hi> from whence is plaine, <hi>that Chriſt Ieſus was learned of the Father to preach by the Spirit, without
<pb facs="tcp:4451:11"/>Human-Learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See further of this in the Epiſtle noted with this marke. <g ref="char:tdagger">‡̶</g>
               </note> and ſo much is plain to them that can beleeve the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> from <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.15. where the Jews admire, ſaying, <hi>How comes this man to know the Scriptures, ſeeing that he was never learned:</hi> from whence it is plain that as he was a Man he was <hi>unlearned</hi> in the <hi>letters</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> though as <hi>God</hi> he knew all things, and by a <hi>divine power,</hi> not <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> ſo much as his own <hi>naturall tongue</hi> by <hi>letter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.7.</note> as in the Synagogue he could take the Book and read: and this doubtleſſe was one cauſe, why the Jewes are ſaid to be <hi>aſtonished</hi> at the <hi>bearing</hi> and <hi>ſeing</hi> of Him, as appeares <hi>Math.</hi> 13.54. &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.22. ſo that from all this my affirmation remaines true, and good, <hi>that if Human-Learning should be it that is there meant by the Apoſtle, then he was to teach the Servant to be above his Myſter,</hi> whenas <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.5.</note> ſaith, <hi>It is enough for the Diſciple to be as his Lord,</hi> and he being <hi>deſtitute</hi> of <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> his Diſciples may well be <hi>without</hi> it alſo, without any offence, and yet preach the Goſpel too. Now, if notwithſtanding all this there be them that will take<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Stephens accuſers</hi> place, and ſtill accuſe me of <hi>Uaſphemy</hi> as they did him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though it may be, they may ſay true words, as that I ſaid that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt was without Human-Learning,</hi> and ſo apply it to him as <hi>God,</hi> whenas I ſpake of him as Man, they may there ſee themſelves ranked among the number of them that are called by the <hi>Spirit of God falſe witneſſes,</hi> as walking in the ſteps of thoſe envious perſons, even ſuch as were alwayes the <hi>murtherers</hi> and <hi>betrayers</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> and his <hi>ſervants:</hi> and they that are ſuch, may be likened to them that being full of <hi>envy,</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Act. 13.45.</note> 
               <hi>ſpake againſt thoſe things that were ſpoken of Paul, contrarying them, and rayling on them:</hi> Marke it, they denyed what he <hi>taught,</hi> but diſproved it not, but ſpake againſt it, and rayled on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo left not till they had bin a meanes to expell them out of their Coaſts; ſo was he, and ſuch like <hi>meaſure</hi> is ſtill to be <hi>expected</hi> to befall ſuch as tread in his ſteps, but it is to be minded that <hi>envious ones</hi> are the <hi>movers</hi> of it: and ſo leaving of it, I come to another <hi>exception,</hi> which is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> How ſuch as are <hi>unlearned,</hi> wilbe able to ſtoppe <hi>the mouthes of gainſayers,</hi> ſeeing the Apoſtle requires of a<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Bishop that he should be able</hi> ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, that it is not the Apoſtles <hi>intent that the mouthes of gainſayers</hi> ſhould be ſtopped by the knowledge of <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>arts,</hi> but that way that himſelfe directs, 1 <hi>Titus</hi> 9. which is <hi>by ſound doctrine,</hi> or by <hi>wholſome doctrine;</hi> ſo then, to goe any other way then thus ſtoppe <hi>their mouthes,</hi> is both an unſound, and an
<pb facs="tcp:4451:11"/>unwholſome courſe: and it were farre <hi>better</hi> in my <hi>judgement</hi> and that according to <hi>Paul, that their mouthes should be left open,</hi> then that they ſhould be <hi>ſtopt</hi> after that manner, and it hath not profited them in the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> meaning of the <hi>word</hi> that have bin exerciſed therin: ſo now it is high time that we, honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>teaching of the Spirit,</hi> ſhould refuſe to meddle with ſuch as goe another way to work, then by <hi>it,</hi> to declare <hi>Gods mind</hi> to us, becauſe it alone is ſufficient <hi>to ſtoppe the mouthes of all gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>They were not able to reſiſt the Spirit</hi> (not the <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>arts</hi>) by which he ſpake, for he uſed none of them, <hi>for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our warfare are not carnall,</hi> and ſo are <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>arts,</hi> and ſuch like, <hi>but yet mighty,</hi> not by man, but through <hi>God, to</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.45.</note> 
               <hi>caſt down holds:</hi> therfore this <hi>weapon</hi> onely is <hi>ſufficient to ſtoppe the mouth of all gaynſayers;</hi> and for ſuch as think it not <hi>ſufficient,</hi> much good let their <hi>Human-Learning</hi> doe them, and <hi>the good Lord give me of his holy Spirit onely, to doe this worke;</hi> and ſo I come to the next <hi>exception,</hi> which is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> That there was the uſe of <hi>tongues</hi> in the Apoſtles times in the Churches, <hi>Act</hi> 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This I grant was <hi>true,</hi> but there we finde that they were the <hi>immediate gifts of God,</hi> freely given and beſtowed on them as other <hi>ſpirituall gifts</hi> were, without their <hi>induſtry</hi> or <hi>paines,</hi> as appeares in divers<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures:</hi> now wherſoever ſuch <hi>gifts</hi> are to be found, them I will freely acknowledge, as being indeed ſutable to the Goſpel, which brings to us freely all good <hi>gifts,</hi> without any labour or paines of ours, and therfore all is ſaid <hi>to be of gift, leaſt any man should boaſt:</hi> but if the <hi>tongues</hi> that are pleaded for, are ſuch as are <hi>attayned</hi> to by <hi>induſtry</hi> and <hi>paines-taking</hi> of our own, then they better ſuit with <hi>works</hi> then <hi>grace,</hi> and ſo are more meet for <hi>Ægypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> then for the Church of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which comes by all her pretious Gifts <hi>gratis,</hi> and therfore ſuch as plead for theſe things, as ſutable to the Miniſters, become in effect ſutable with<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> who would have obtayned the <hi>gift of the Spirit, by money,</hi> which there was the <hi>gift of tongues,</hi> and if theſe <hi>tongues</hi> pleaded for, be the ſame, they are all attayned by <hi>money,</hi> and if this be ſo good a way now, why doth <hi>Peter</hi> ſo evilly intreat him, for deſiring that for <hi>money,</hi> which all afterwards by theſe pleas were therby to obtaine: But <hi>Peter</hi> we ſee perceives him to be in the <hi>gall of bitterneſſe, and the bond of iniquity,</hi> that ſhould offer to ſeeke to obtaine the <hi>gift of Gods Spirit</hi> that way: and if they be <hi>Human-excellencies,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:12"/>then of <hi>neceſſity</hi> the courſe is to be <hi>repented</hi> of alſo, that any ſhould offer to bring any <hi>humane</hi> thing to <hi>Gods word,</hi> when as it is ſo expreſly forbidden us, <hi>that we put nothing therto, nor take any thing therfrom;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.6.</note> 
               <hi>Put nothing to his Word, leaſt he reprove thee and thou be found a lyer.</hi> Now there is nothing but the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> goe together, therfore they are lyable to <hi>Gods reproofe,</hi> which is<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 50.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>tearing in pieces.</hi> Therfore let all ſuch as ſtand for ſuch <hi>learning</hi> to bring men to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>Gods word,</hi> mind whether <hi>Peters exhortation</hi> to <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> ought not to take place with them, namely to<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.22.</note> 
               <hi>repent of this their wickedneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. and acknowledge the <hi>Spirit of God freely beſtowed, to be the alone furnisher of us to that which is right in his ſight,</hi> without which none haue part or fellowſhip of this buſineſſe in <hi>underſtanding</hi> and <hi>unfolding</hi> of the things of <hi>God,</hi> and ſo I come to another <hi>exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> Suppoſe two Men, both alike indued with <hi>grace</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and alike <hi>gifted</hi> by His <hi>Spirit,</hi> the one <hi>a learned man,</hi> and the other an <hi>unlearned man,</hi> which of theſe two ſhould be choſen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſtry of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>The unlearned man:</hi> For theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>God reſpect no mans perſon:</hi> now if <hi>God</hi> ſhould take the <hi>learned man,</hi> then he muſt be <hi>reſpected</hi> above the other for it, if he be of right and due to be preferred, which is wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe once to thinke of him, for all are alike in that reſpect: but the <hi>Scripture</hi> tells us, and that for good reaſon, <hi>that without any reſpect at all, he of his good pleaſure, and that no flesh should glory, hath choſen the foolish things and the vile things in mans account; he hath choſen the</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>foolish things of this world to confound the wiſe:</hi> then if, <hi>God</hi> have ſo <hi>choſen,</hi> let him have his own <hi>choyce,</hi> it is meet he ſhould, for his <hi>choyce</hi> is the <hi>beſt;</hi> and the end why he hath ſo <hi>choſen,</hi> is, <hi>that he might confound the wiſe,</hi> and ſo<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Isay.</hi> 29.13.</note> 
               <hi>fulfill his words</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="‡̶" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>expreſſeth;</hi> and thus he <hi>chooſeth</hi> not onely for <hi>ſalvation</hi> but for <hi>miniſtration,</hi> the<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>foolish</hi> in Mans account. <hi>Paul</hi> it ſeems was ſo <hi>foolish</hi> in theirs and others account,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Col.</hi> 11.1.</note> in his <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> as that they could ſcarce ſuffer it, and this ſence muſt needs be good, though the place be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Gods choyce to ſalvation onely,</hi> which cannot be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe as we may ſee <hi>Pauls argument</hi> is about<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>preaching of the Goſpel,</hi> going onwards in oppoſing the Scribe and <hi>diſputer</hi> of this world, to them that were not ſuch, and ſo comes to declare among whom it was, that the <hi>Lord</hi> made his <hi>choyce,</hi> and that was among the <hi>foolish</hi> in the worlds eye: but as I ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:4451:12"/>before, take the other for the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and the <hi>point</hi> remaines <hi>true,</hi> becauſe, <hi>that of ſuch as God chooſeth to ſalvation of them, he chooſeth Miniſters, and for ſalvation it is granted he chooſeth the foolish,</hi> then it muſt needs follow, <hi>that out of the foolish alſo he chooſeth Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, And this indeed is moſt ſutable to the Goſpel,<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.</note> which is it ſelfe <hi>ſimpicity,</hi> and appeares to the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of man ſo to be, and it is not meet our Saviour ſaith to put <hi>contraries</hi> together, <hi>as a new piece into an old garment, nor new wine into old veſſels,</hi> but to have all things ſutable. Therfore ſeeing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is<note n="‡̶" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>foolishneſſe,</hi> therfore it is meet he ſhould have <hi>foolish Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>wiſe worlds account,</hi> yea and in his <hi>ſervants</hi> too, whenas <hi>they ſee as man ſees, and not as doth the Lord,</hi> For thus was it of old ſubject to <hi>Samuel</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> Prophet, whenas the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent him to the houſe of <hi>Ishay, to anoynt him a King,</hi> he <hi>ſeeing as a man doth,</hi> he ſaid,<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſurely the Lords anoynted is before me,</hi> but we find that the <hi>Lord corrects that,</hi> and tells him, <hi>it was not ſo, the more unlikely man, and the unthought of one, was he that God had choſen to himſelfe,</hi> and ſo is it here, <hi>we are not to ſee as man ſees,</hi> but <hi>as the Lord directs us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>God chooſeth theſe things in oppoſition to others, to aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the wiſdome of man:</hi> When the<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Councel</hi> perceived <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were <hi>unlearned men,</hi> and <hi>without knowledge, they marveyled,</hi> and were <hi>amazed:</hi> And ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>He</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>catcheth the wiſe in their own craft:</hi> they thinke that all <hi>knowledge</hi> lyes in their breaſts. Now the <hi>Lord</hi> he comes and makes <hi>fooles wiſe,</hi> and ſo <hi>catcheth</hi> them, manifeſting <hi>that their thoughts be but vaine, in thinking that the wiſe be them that God hath choſen;</hi> for it is not ſo, <hi>for he hath choſen the foolish to confound the wiſe,</hi> and therfore ſuch as are <hi>godly wiſe,</hi> ſhould chooſe <hi>Gods wiſe,</hi> but the worlds <hi>foolish things</hi> for His, ſerve before the <hi>worlds wiſe ones:</hi> and ſo I come to another <hi>exception,</hi> which is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>5</label> If it be <hi>ſanctified,</hi> it muſt needs be a <hi>good helpe to the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is true, if it be <hi>ſanctified,</hi> ſo it is, But how or where doth that appeare that ever it was <hi>ſanctified?</hi> Hath not the <hi>Lord</hi> long agone told us by his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 19.15.</note> 
               <hi>Prophet,</hi> and wiſhed his to behold it, <hi>that he would doe a marveylous worke,</hi> and then he doubles it againe, <hi>even a marveylous worke and a wonder,</hi> and then all comes to this, <hi>that he would cauſe to perish, and deſtroy the wiſdome of the wiſe, and caſt away the underſtanding of the prudent;</hi> and here if we could ſee, we might all of us ſtay our <hi>wondering</hi> at this <hi>ſtrange thing,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:13"/>and conſider, the <hi>Lord</hi> tells us, <hi>it is a marveylous worke and a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and ſo our <hi>wondering</hi> and <hi>marveyling,</hi> how theſe things come ſo to be, is but a fulfilling of <hi>Gods word;</hi> and men might reſt in it, and ſee in the next words, <hi>that it is a wo to them for the former abuſe of the ſame:</hi> and ſo now as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he would curſe their bleſſings, and that he had done it already:</hi> to both which<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> agrees the Apoſtle from <hi>Iſay,</hi> and concludes alſo <hi>that God hath deſtroyed it:</hi> and in another place tells us, <hi>that it is emnity with God.</hi> How ſhall any dare ſay then, <hi>it is ſanctified,</hi> whenas ſo plain a <hi>curſe</hi> is on it, as that we are wiſhed to beware of being<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by it:</hi> Now are we wiſhed any where to beware of being ſpoyled by that which is <hi>ſanctified to us,</hi> in a <hi>ſpirituall way.</hi> Now theſe things can be <hi>ſanctified</hi> no further then they are of uſe, and that is but in a worldly way: for a <hi>ſpirituall uſe</hi> they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed from it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> Now another <hi>exception</hi> from theſe things thus minded is, That by this all <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> ſeems utterly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, that it followes not; becauſe it is not to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this way, that therfore it is not of any uſe; for I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it in it ſelfe to be a good thing, and good in its proper place,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>from</hi> 6. <hi>to</hi> 10.</note> which is for the repayring of that § <hi>decay which came upon man for ſinne:</hi> ſo, I ſay, it is of good uſe, for the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that loſſe, and ſo fit for States-men, Phyſicians, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, and Gentlemen, yea, all men ſo farre as they can attaine to it, are as men beyond and above others that are without it, yea, and beyond all other excellencies that this world can afford: but bring it once to be a <hi>help to underſtand the mind of God in the holy Scriptures,</hi> and there it is <hi>deteſtable filth, droſſe</hi> and <hi>dung</hi> in that reſpect, and ſo good for nothing, but<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.21</note> 
               <hi>deſtroy and cauſe men to erre,</hi> as we have ſeen before: It fares with it, as I perceive, as it doth with Fire, keep it in the Chymney, and it ſerves as a good <hi>bleſſing of God,</hi> for good and neceſſary uſes, but let it once come into the roofe of the houſe, and it deſtroyes all, becauſe it is not in its proper place: ſo it is here for this thing, among men, for <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>worldly imployments,</hi> it is good; But bring it once <hi>to the perfiting of the Goſpel,</hi> and it will be found to be the ſpoyling of it.</p>
            <p>And yet further ſo farre doe I acknowledge <hi>tongues</hi> to be of uſe, as to yeeld us the <hi>tranſlation,</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> out of one <hi>language</hi> into another, without which we that are <hi>unlearned</hi> could not come to have the <hi>letter</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> and ſo farre there
<pb facs="tcp:4451:13"/>as a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of it for that uſe: but that man which can foe doe, is ever the more able to <hi>underſtand</hi> the <hi>ſpirituall meaning</hi> iof the <hi>word</hi> thereby, that I deny, and withall doe affirme that an <hi>underſtanding man may through the teaching of the Spirit know the mind of God,</hi> which the other may never reach unto, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.</note> ſaying of our Saviour; <hi>To you it is given to know the Myſteries, the ſecrets of the Kingdome of heaven,</hi> to you his <hi>ſimple Diſciples it is given,</hi> but to others, the <hi>learned Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> it was not given: But in this caſe it may fare as it did with thoſe that <hi>built Noahs</hi> Arke, they made a place of <hi>ſafeguard</hi> for <hi>others,</hi> but were <hi>drowned themſelves:</hi> ſo theſe men may prepare a <hi>good helpe</hi> for <hi>others,</hi> but themſelves be altogether without the <hi>benefit</hi> of it: A Lantherne you know is of good uſe, to contain the Candle, but let one carry it in a darke night, and it will doe him no pleaſure without a Candle lighted in it; of the ſame uſe is the <hi>letter</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> it is but as a Lautherne or Candle without <hi>light.</hi> Now the <hi>Spirit</hi> is the <hi>light</hi> of the <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and ſo is the Apoſtles<note n="‡" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>oppoſition:</hi> ſuch men then in that reſpect may be a <hi>help to others,</hi> and yet when all is done be but <hi>caſtawayes themſelves,</hi> ſeeing as we have before ſeen, the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and Babylonians</hi> in this kind of <hi>learning</hi> did <hi>excell.</hi> And it is none other bleſſing then what the Pope, Cardinalls, and other profeſſed enemies of the <hi>truth</hi> (as all for the generall confeſſe them to be) have in as great a meaſure, and beyond many others that profeſſe to know the <hi>truth,</hi> and ſtand ſtifly for this as a ſpeciall <hi>helpe to underſtand the true meaning of the Lord in the word,</hi> which if it be ſo, then by their own grants they have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of them, and ſo are to be reverenced of themſelves, to have more <hi>knowledge</hi> in it then they: ſo then, they are to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their <hi>errour, in counting themſelves wiſe above what is meet,</hi> or elſe muſt be forced to confeſſe, <hi>that that learning is ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayleable for finding out of the mind of God.</hi> Neither for all this would I have any to conclude of me, as ſome affirme, <hi>that I hold all Learned men to be excluded from the ſpirituall meaning of the Word, God</hi> forbid, for,</p>
            <p>Though the Apoſtle<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.</note> ſay, <hi>not many of ſeverall rankes,</hi> yet he ſaith not, <hi>there is none,</hi> but yet <hi>not many:</hi> There was one <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.43.</note> 
               <hi>Arimathea;</hi> One † <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> One Deputy<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Surgeus Paulus a prudent man,</hi> and divers of<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>the Prieſts.</hi> But this was not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, for it is hard for ſuch men to entertaine the <hi>truth. Gods</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way is among the <hi>foolish</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.28. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.5. <hi>with Mat.</hi> 11.5.</note> 
               <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>vile;</hi> ſo that when as the <hi>wiſe, rich, noble</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> come to receive the Goſpel,
<pb facs="tcp:4451:14"/>they then come to make themſelves <hi>equall with them of the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.26.</note> 
               <hi>lower ſort, the foolish, vile and unlearned,</hi> for thoſe be the <hi>true</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 51.1.</note> 
               <hi>heyres</hi> of it; and therfore it was not in vaine, that <hi>Iames</hi> ſayd,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Hearken, my beloved Brethren, hath not God choſen the poore,</hi> he well ſaw that the <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>carnall</hi> were dull of <hi>hearing</hi> of this <hi>matter,</hi> but yet he tells them <hi>God hath choſen the poore of this world to be rich in Faith,</hi> and upon this conſideration it is that he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>I am.</hi> 1.9.10</note> 
               <hi>Brother of high degree to rejoyce in that he was made low,</hi> that is, <hi>brought in his mind, and account equall with the poore, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe never the higher for any ſuch excellencies:</hi> and ſo <hi>the Brother of low degree, to rejoyce in that he is exalted,</hi> that is, <hi>that he was made a</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>King and Prieſt unto God, and was ſet in heavenly places with Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo as the one is made <hi>low</hi> in reſpect of any <hi>fleshly conſidence</hi> he hath in ſuch things, the other is <hi>exalted,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>out wardly poore,</hi> by being in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and ſo they both meet in one; but now by reaſon <hi>of the ſmoke that is riſen out of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> and <hi>that the Devil is</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>caſt out of heaven, and all his Angels with him to the Earth,</hi> which Angels were the <hi>fallen</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>Starres that he drew after his tayle,</hi> that now he hath by reaſon of them <hi>hatched</hi> ſince a Religion in the world, as that he would have the <hi>wiſe,</hi> the <hi>rich,</hi> the <hi>noble,</hi> the <hi>learned</hi> the onely ones, and the <hi>poore</hi> muſt be beholden to them, whenas this is like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe directly to oppoſe <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo, as that we may truly ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Lord who hath beleeved our report, or to whom is the arme of the Lord revealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>7</label> But it is yet further Objected to be the manner of ſuch as canot themſelves attaine to that <hi>excellencie</hi> that is in another, to diſparage that in them that ſo they might advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This I confeſſe is a <hi>carnall courſe</hi> that ſuch as are themſelves fleſhly are ſubject to take, and it may as well be my fault as anothers, But yet I profeſſe in the preſence of the <hi>Lord</hi> that I doe not allow my ſelfe in any ſuch courſe. Neither doth ſuch an <hi>exception</hi> as this beſeeme a man <hi>that is led by the Spirit of Truth,</hi> for to make againſt any <hi>ſervant of God,</hi> that profeſſeth <hi>oppoſition</hi> to ſuch things, as profeſſing to be led thereto by the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> For it ſavours ſtrongly of the <hi>flesh,</hi> and is too ſutable to the <hi>practiſe of Reprobates,</hi> whoſe <hi>practiſe</hi> is to take <hi>things in the evil part,</hi> wheras <hi>love</hi> by which <hi>all the Saints should judge, judges the beſt of things,</hi> till ſuch time it can eſpie any cauſe ſo to doe. And for the <hi>lifting up</hi> of my <hi>ſelfe,</hi> to be ſure <hi>if</hi> I ſo doe, <hi>Gods word</hi> it is, <hi>that he will plucke the mighty from his ſeat,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:14"/>and then you may be ſure that according to his <hi>word</hi> my <hi>fall will be farre greater then my exaltation can poſſibly be,</hi> and therfore it were beſt for all ſuch as ſo conceive, to <hi>commit the judgement to the Lord,</hi> and themſelves <hi>judge nothing before the time, not ſpeake no more preſumptuouſly: let not arrogancie come out of your mouth, for the Lord is a God of knowledge, and by him enterpriſes are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</hi> But yet after this manner of reaſoning, <hi>carnall men</hi> may overthrow the whole Goſpell: For whereas the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhews <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt was without forme, or beauty, or any ſuch thing, wherfore he should be deſired,</hi> the <hi>carnall man</hi> will ſoon ſay no other but ſuch a one would be ſo <hi>foolish,</hi> as to part from <hi>honours, riches, credit,</hi> and ſuch like, to indure ſo much ſorrow and need not, and whereas the Apoſtle<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> ſaith, <hi>that he tooke on him the forme of a ſervant,</hi> the would ſoon anſwer, and good reaſon why, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not be a Maſter: and wheras it is ſaid, <hi>he choſe the poore,</hi> that will they ſay, he muſt needs do; <hi>and the foolish,</hi> for none of the <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> would be ſo <hi>ſimple,</hi> as to <hi>follow him:</hi> and wheras he ſaith, <hi>love not the world, nor the things in it,</hi> good cauſe why will they ſay, for ſuch <hi>fooles</hi> as you, know not how to get it, or elſe, to be ſure, you would love it as well as others. And thus have I given you a glympſe, how that by this manner of <hi>carnall arguing,</hi> we might overthrow our own <hi>ſalvation, and ſit down in the very vale and shadow of death,</hi> as <hi>full of darkneſſe,</hi> as this <hi>argument</hi> is <hi>deſtitute of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having Anſwered to ſuch <hi>exceptions</hi> as I know of made againſt this <hi>truth:</hi> I come now to ſuch Uſes as it ſhall afford us.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> The firſt is</p>
            <p>To diſcover to us the <hi>depth of the great Woe, that the world lyes under,</hi> ſet forth and <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. <hi>from</hi> 1. <hi>to</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>revealed to us,</hi> in which the <hi>word of the Lord" is fulfilled,</hi> and men ſee it not: and this you know the <hi>Scripture</hi> in ſundry places makes the <hi>depth of a judgement,</hi> as in <hi>Hoſea, Ephraim is ſaid to have here and there gray hayres, and yet he ſaw them not;</hi> and in this we know was the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of that<note n="‡" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>great Iudgement, that men should confidently take lyes for truth,</hi> this is there made the <hi>depth of their woe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 42.</note> And the like is <hi>manifeſted</hi> § elſe where, by the ſame Apoſtle, declaring, <hi>that though they ſpeake lyes, yet they were ſo ſeared in their Conſciences, as that they felt, nor feared no danger that they were in,</hi> no more <hi>then the man that lying drunke did, though he lay ſleeping on the top of the Maſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.35.35.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo ready to be drowned, yet he feared it not;</hi> and yet ſuch is the caſe, the Sun and the Ayre being <hi>darkened,</hi> their <hi>condition</hi> muſt needs be <hi>wofull:</hi> and yet this is the caſe of the <hi>inhabitants of the
<pb facs="tcp:4451:15"/>Earth,</hi> that they cannot be brought to <hi>beleeve,</hi> but that they are in a very good caſe, though <hi>that the light of the glorious Goſpel, which is the Image of God, doe not shine unto them,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.6.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. Now that by which this Sun is ſaid to be <hi>darkened, is the ſmoke of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> and that we ſhall find to be the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>power of the falſe Church,</hi> called by the name of the <hi>Bottomleſſe pit.</hi> And that this may the <hi>better appear,</hi> we find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 6.4.1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.11.12. <hi>with.</hi> 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8</note> place in the <hi>Scripture, manifeſting the glory of God, and his power to be his ſmoke:</hi> Now becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>ſmoke</hi> in his <hi>Temple,</hi> ſo hath <hi>Gods adverſary</hi> in his Temple alſo, or rather, his <hi>bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit:</hi> After his <hi>ſmoke,</hi> in <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.2.3. <hi>there follows power;</hi> and if you looke in the 7, 8, and 9. verſes, there is their <hi>glory;</hi> and it doth further appeare by the 13th Chap. and the 3. verſe, <hi>that it was ſo great power and glory,</hi> as <hi>that all the world wondered, and admired it;</hi> and yet this <hi>Ieſus Chriſt accounts a great wo and plague to them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.10.11</note> Now part of this <hi>woe,</hi> I beleeve is this <hi>learning,</hi> which we have here in queſtion, for as we have before mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, <hi>the Sun light of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt alows not,</hi> for the <hi>glory of Chriſts Doctrine is, that it is of the Spirits teaching:</hi> for when we behold the <hi>glory of the Lord</hi> in the moſt <hi>perfecteſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12.</note> ſo as <hi>we are changed thereinto from glory to glory,</hi> yet all is from <hi>the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> ſeeing that he is the <hi>promiſed Comforter, that is to teach us all good things belonging to our perfection.</hi> Then it muſt needs follow that is a <hi>ſmokey power,</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> flowing <hi>from the Kingdome of Sathan, and ſo a part of the tayle that the</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>Dragon drew the Starres withall after him:</hi> and hence comes it to paſſe, that now inſtead of the <hi>Spirits teaching,</hi> according to <hi>Peters propheſie,</hi> here are a <hi>generation</hi> that doe ariſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>which privily bring in damnable errours, and ſo for that end forſaking the Spirit of truth, they ſpeake lyes through hypocriſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo witneſſeth they ſhould doe, pretending now <hi>that the true and right way for underſtanding the Scriptures and mind of God was, that men for that end muſt learne a part from others, onely for that worke, and ſo to be taught in Tongues, and divers Languages, and have their wits exerciſed in Arts and Sciences humane:</hi> and ſo ſuch a flouriſh beares this in mans <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> as that it ſeems the onely way that can be for a man to be made fit for this worke: ſo that before while the Angels kept their ſtation in <hi>heaven, the Spirits ſimple teaching was judged ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient without theſe things for this worke,</hi> they now being <hi>fallen</hi> from thence to the <hi>earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>and having the key of the bottomleſse pit,</hi> thence it being opened, now ariſeth up<note n="*" place="margin">See Iohn Bale on Rev. <hi>9.1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude more of Heathen Philoſophers. Theſe are the <hi>foure An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb facs="tcp:4451:15"/>that ſtand on the foure corners of the earth, holding the foure winds that they should not blow on the Earth, neither on the Sea, neither on any Tree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.1.</note> as being thoſe that have the whole power of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their hand, not ſuffering <hi>any to blow but who they pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>ſo doe withold the truth in unrighteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>declalaring thereby they be under the wrath of God:</hi> and they ſeem to yeeld theſe Starrey Principles, very fitting in their own underſtanding, <hi>better</hi> to furniſh them with <hi>fitneſſe to open the mind of God,</hi> then His <hi>Spirit</hi> can doe; whereas before, whenas the <hi>perfect teachings of the holy Spirit</hi> was in force, theſe men of all others were by reaſon of their <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>wiſdome,</hi> the moſt <hi>untutableſt men</hi> that were in the world for the receiving of the <hi>truth,</hi> as appeares by the teſtimony of <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.18.</note> and is not yet for all <hi>the great Sun light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> which theſe men profeſſe, they have theſe <hi>blacke ſmokey principles ſtill</hi> ſo ſtiffly ſtood for, as that there is no removing of men from the high <hi>conceit</hi> that they have of them. And doth not this ſufficiently declare as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that God hath blinded the minds of men, ſo as they cannot ſee, but are ſo much the blinder becauſe they ſay they ſee:</hi> and hence came it to paſſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.41.</note> that I for mentioning <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and ſuch like, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded how I came by the knowledge of that, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> if not by <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Learning?</hi> with <hi>contempt</hi> caſt upon it, as if that which I had from them, being <hi>Humane Learned Men,</hi> was of it ſelfe ſufficient to overthrow the matter which I had there delivered.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwered then as I doe ſtill, it was none other but as <hi>Paul</hi> mentioned to the <hi>Athenians their own Poets,</hi> and yet for all that he was as <hi>great</hi> an <hi>enemy to Human-Learning</hi> as I, and <hi>greater</hi> too.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17</note> And it is to be minded, as I have before declared, <hi>that I doe not oppoſe the knowledge of Humane things, nor yet deny but that we may be acquainted with their ſayings,</hi> as the Apoſtle himſelfe, and our Saviour was, yea and that ſomtimes we make uſe of them too, as occaſion requires, as I have done here, though ſparingly, and but ſeldome, and when it is, that it be of <hi>great uſe,</hi> as it was at thoſe 3 <hi>times</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> did uſe them, and no more,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12.</note> that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in all the <hi>Scripture.</hi> Now this you ſee <hi>the Spirit teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and therefore it cannot properly be called <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> eſpecially in my ſence that I have to doe withall, which is to oppoſe that which is <hi>maintained, to make men fitting to open the mind of God in his word,</hi> which is <hi>by the learning of tongues and arts, as of neceſſity,</hi> wheras this is uſed but by the <hi>by,</hi> and not to find out the <hi>Truth with,</hi> but it being ſufficiently before proved, by
<pb facs="tcp:4451:16"/>themſelves alſo. It is the <hi>Spirits</hi> order to gaine there <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement</hi> of it, and this is no other <hi>learning,</hi> but what every man without any Scholerſhip (as ye call it) may attaine unto, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that that is ſo much <hi>gloryed in,</hi> is, <hi>that a man is able aptly to ſpeak according to art and knowledge in the Sciences,</hi> and this is it by which men yet ſtill are <hi>hatched</hi> and bred up,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. <hi>to.</hi> 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4.</note> and this I beleeve was the meanes of bringing in all thoſe abhominable <hi>errours that the Earth hath drunke in, both in Doctrine and Practiſe, and ſo have occaſined thoſe noyſome luſts that drown men in perdition, that the man of God is to flie, as beſt beſeeming the tayle of the Dragon,</hi> and ſuting with this <hi>great woe</hi> which is <hi>further manifeſted,</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the Miniſters of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> and thoſe together. Now what marks they be known by, you may read in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. from the the 3. to the 11. verſe, where as in a Looking-glaſſe, you may behold the <hi>true picture,</hi> both of the one, and of the other: <hi>By them we approve our ſelves as the Miniſters of Chriſt, and give none occaſion, why our Miniſtry should be reprooved,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, In much Patience, in Afflictions, in Neceſſities in Diſtreſſes, in ſtrips, in Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, in Tumults, in Labour, in Watchings, in Faſtings, by purenes, by knowledge, by long-ſuffering, by kindneſſe, by the Holy Ghoſt, by love unfeigned, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteouſneſse, on the right hand, and on the left, by honour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, by evill report, and good report, as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceivers and yet true; as unknown, and yet known, as dying, and yet behold we live, as chaſtened, and not killed, as ſorrowfull, and yet alway rejoycing, as poore, and yet making many rich, as having nothing and yet poſseſſing all things.</hi> Theſe ye ſee are the marks by which <hi>Paul</hi> approves himſelfe with his <hi>fellow labourers,</hi> to be the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi> Now the quite <hi>contrary</hi> may be read in thoſe that profeſſe themſelves ſo to be: They diſprove themſelves to be the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> in all theſe things; <hi>where is their patient bearing with the contrary minded,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſervants of God</hi> ſhould doe? and where are <hi>their afflictions</hi> which <hi>they ſuffer, with their neceſſities and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes?</hi> are they not for the moſt part <hi>full of all outward neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?</hi> What are they in <hi>diſtreſſe for?</hi> How many <hi>ſtripes</hi> do they <hi>ſuffer,</hi> or ſhall have need ſo to doe, be they but <hi>obſervant</hi> of their Canonicall <hi>obedience?</hi> How many, nay, where are any <hi>impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> that they <hi>ſuffer,</hi> or at leaſt need to doe, if they live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own Laws? And for <hi>tumults,</hi> they are ſo farre from abiding any, as that they be farre more ready to make <hi>them</hi> againſt <hi>others,</hi> then to indure <hi>them themſelves:</hi> and for their <hi>labours,</hi> which what he means you may perceive by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12.
<pb facs="tcp:4451:16"/>and that to be ſure they are <hi>guiltleſse</hi> of: and ſo for their <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>faſtings,</hi> and all the reſt being duly conſidered of, we may read the <hi>quite contrary fulfill'd in them,</hi> ſo that of <hi>neceſſity</hi> there will appeare as voyd a difference, as is betwixt <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and thoſe perſons more fitly futing that deſcription, belonging to the<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. <hi>9.</hi> from <hi>7.</hi> to. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Locuſts,</hi> then with this <hi>deſcription</hi> here of the<note n="‡" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 <hi>feom</hi> 3. <hi>to</hi> 11.</note> Apoſtle, ſo farre are they from what they <hi>pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> to be, as that the words of the <hi>Prophet</hi> come truly to be <hi>fullfild</hi> in them, <hi>that their</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 47, 10.</note> 
               <hi>wiſdome and their knowledge perverts them, or cauſes them to erre, and is the wickedneſſe they truſt unto:</hi> and this is it <hi>that lifts them up in their own conceits, ſo farre, as that they think in their hearts</hi> and ſtick not to ſay alſo <hi>with their tongues, that they are for the miniſtration of the word,</hi> and none elſe: and the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, <hi>that their wiſdome and knowledge is the cauſe of this their errour,</hi> and they ſay, <hi>it is the meanes of right underſtanding:</hi> now whether is to be <hi>beleeved, God</hi> or they, let all judge, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when as we ſee, <hi>that the Lord himſelfe is againſt them for it,</hi> in denying others he denyes them, ſaying, <hi>therfore shall evill come upon thee, and thou shalt not know where it ariſeth,</hi> &amp;c. all which declares the <hi>depth of the woe</hi> they lye under; for is not this a <hi>wofull thing, that of that which God hath made a curſe, men should make a bleſſing,</hi> and that againſt his will, and ſay that his mind cannot be known, what can be more againſt him.</p>
            <p>In the next place, that being ſo,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that men taught by Gods ſpirit are through it ſufficiently made able to know his mind in word,</hi> then it <hi>teacheth</hi> us not to <hi>account</hi> any man any whit the nearer <hi>to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Scriptures by any humane excellencies,</hi> but rather let us be ſuſpitious of him that hath them, for the ſame: eſpecially if he make uſe of them in thoſe things, for as we have ſeen they be dangerous to be leaned unto. <hi>It is</hi> his high time that now we ſhould all <hi>awake from ſleep, and watch in the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.19.</note> and ſo <hi>let the Lord have all the prayſe and glory of his own grace: Not unto us, Not unto us, but to his name be all the glory, ſeeing it is he onely that doth great things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo it may teach all men to ceaſe pinning of their <hi>faith</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſleeves of <hi>learned men,</hi> for there is no good cauſe why we ſhould ſo doe, but to <hi>ſee with our own eyes,</hi> ſeeing <hi>that the juſt is to live by his own Faith,</hi> and to beleeve what the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſaid, which is, <hi>that he hath</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>hid thoſe things,</hi> that is, <hi>the myſteries of the Goſpell</hi> (among which, this which now is declared is one) <hi>from the wiſe and learned,</hi> and this I verily beleeve, is the <hi>wholſome doctrine of the Goſpel,</hi> and which hath againſt it <hi>the wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:4451:17"/>oppoſing and denying of it</hi> to be ſo, and ſo confirming the words of our Saviour: therfore need we not to <hi>wait</hi> for their <hi>witneſſe</hi> to it, but to be glad, and rejoyce to ſee his ſaying made <hi>true, That he will reveale them to Babes,</hi> that is, <hi>ſimple things in the worlds eye and account,</hi> and with this conſideration <hi>to overlooke all contempt that can be caſt upon us for the ſame:</hi> For ſo is it now with men, that they judge that <hi>nothing</hi> is <hi>hid</hi> from ſuch and ſuch, when as we are to expect the <hi>fullfilling</hi> of the Prophecie of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>Zachary, that the Lord will cut off the names of the Idols and the uncleane ſpirits of the Land, and that while they Prophecie their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother that begat them, shall run them through with the ſword of the Spirit, and ſay, that they shall not live, becauſe they told lyes in the name of the Lord,</hi> and then ſhall they be <hi>ashamed of their viſion;</hi> and it then ſhall be known, that their <hi>garments,</hi> by which they be <hi>known</hi> and taken <hi>knowledge</hi> of to be <hi>Miniſters,</hi> are <hi>garments of deceit:</hi> and at that day ſuch Prophets, <hi>shall be ashamed of themſelves,</hi> as that they ſhall <hi>diſclaime themſelves</hi> for very <hi>shame,</hi> to ſtand in any <hi>relation</hi> to ſuch Prophets, as<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.4.5</note> there the Prophet ſhews, whenas their neareſt <hi>friends with contempt shall refuſe them, and run them through,</hi> ſaying, <hi>thou toldeſt us lyes in the name of the Lord;</hi> ſuch <hi>light</hi> it ſeems ſhall then appeare, as that they themſelves ſhall count him no <hi>Prophet,</hi> that is ſo made by mans <hi>teaching:</hi> Now this <hi>teaching</hi> in queſtion, is but <hi>mans teaching,</hi> and therfore whenas the cleare <hi>light</hi> appeares, they ſhalbe <hi>ashamed</hi> of it, though now they preferre it.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration alſo miniſters matter of <hi>thankefullneſſe to God</hi> on our parts,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> for his exceeding <hi>kindneſſe</hi> towards us in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> for that he is pleaſed to reveale <hi>theſe great Myſteries,</hi> to ſuch <hi>meane</hi> and <hi>ſimple things as we are,</hi> whenas he <hi>conceales them from the wiſe and prudent:</hi> This uſe<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe makes, and gives us to underſtand the true cauſe why, and that he makes not any <hi>excellencie</hi> in them, more then was in others, but onely according to the <hi>nature</hi> of the Goſpell, <hi>the grod pleaſure of God,</hi> which is indeed the onely ground <hi>of all our happineſſe,</hi> and bleſſed muſt needs all thoſe be, that can with our Saviour truly conclude with the ſame. And ſo I come to the next point; for having found out <hi>who be the Learned-men</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> here intends, which is, <hi>they that are taught by the Spirit of God:</hi> then it muſt needs follow, that they that are not ſuch, <hi>are the perverters of theſe and all other Scriptures to their own deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and ſo this is another <hi>obſervation,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſuch as are deſtitute of the Spirits teaching, though furnish
<pb facs="tcp:4451:17"/>with</hi> Human-Learning <hi>are the perverters and wreſters of theſe and all other Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>truth</hi> of this Concluſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares plainly confirmed to us in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>Phariſees,</hi> as our Saviour declares in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars plainly diſcovering the<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 23. <hi>from</hi> 16. <hi>to</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>blindneſſe</hi> of theſe <hi>learned teachers,</hi> in eſteeming and preferring of things leſſe in themſelves, above ſuch as were farre greater, as the proportion is made betwixt the <hi>gold of the Temple, and the Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Altar and that which was offred thereon:</hi> and ſo blind were they that they counted that moſt <hi>holy,</hi> which the <hi>Temple</hi> and the <hi>Altar</hi> made to be <hi>holy;</hi> and the ſame<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 15. <hi>from</hi> 3. <hi>to</hi> 7.</note> elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here appeares, that for all their <hi>learning,</hi> they taught directly againſt the <hi>mind of God</hi> in his <hi>word.</hi> We may ſee the ſame farther commended to us in <hi>Barteſus</hi> one full of all<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in this kind, but a <hi>turner from the Faith,</hi> and not to it, and a <hi>perverter of the ſtraight wayes of God.</hi> The like is to be obſerved in,<note n="‚‘‚" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe</hi> of whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>that would be Doctors of the Law, and yet knew not what they ſaid, nor whereof they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffirmed,</hi> ſo wiſe their <hi>Humane-Learning</hi> did helpe to make them.</p>
            <p>Now from the <hi>word of God</hi> good Reaſons may be obſerved, further to confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e this, as firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Becauſe nothing but the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> can bring any to the <hi>true knowledge of the word of God,</hi> and ſo ſaith the<note n="‘‚" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 2.12.</note> Apoſtle, <hi>We have received the Spirit of God, that we may know the things that are given us of God;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21.</note> tells us, <hi>that no Scripture is of any private interpretation,</hi> but in oppoſition to that, the Apoſtle ſets the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and oppoſes it to the <hi>will</hi> of Man, and ſo declares that the <hi>Spirits interpretation,</hi> where it is, is a <hi>publique interpretation</hi> and not <hi>private;</hi> and that Men, though indued with <hi>great learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> having not the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> can give but a <hi>private interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> according to the Apoſtles <hi>intent:</hi> let men judge what they will though it be the Pope, and all his Councels of Cardinals and Biſhops, and the reſt of that <hi>learned rabble,</hi> yet they being deſtitute of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> can give but a <hi>private interpretation</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles mind: whereas if a Man have the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> though he be a <hi>Pedler, Tinker, Chimney-ſweeper,</hi> or COBLER, he may by the helpe of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> give a more <hi>publique interpretation,</hi> then they all, for as <note n="“" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of <hi>love,</hi> the ſame is to be ſaid of the <hi>Spirit, though men did ſpeake with the tongues of Men and Angels, and knew all ſecrets, and had all knowledge, yet this is but as a ſounding braſſe, or tinckling Cymball</hi> without the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Another Reaſon is, becauſe this was one end of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4451:18"/>His comming into the world, <hi>that they that</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.39.</note> 
               <hi>ſee might be made blind,</hi> and this clearely appeares in the Phariſees, thoſe <hi>learned wiſe men</hi> that counted the common people as <hi>accurſed,</hi> becauſe not knowing the Law, and they themſelves <hi>ſeeing, bleſſed ones:</hi> and therfore<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 7.48.</note> ſay they, <hi>Do any of the Rulers, or Phariſes beleeve in him,</hi> as touching, that the Rulers and Phariſes muſt needs know the <hi>Truth,</hi> whenas theſe were <hi>blind guides,</hi> as ſaith our Saviour, and ſo much<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> theſe took notice of that he ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hem; and ſo alſo thoſe that were <hi>blind</hi> in <hi>mans ſight,</hi> as was the <hi>blind man</hi> there ſpoken of, <hi>He ſees the gift of God, and beleeves in Ieſus Chriſt for his ſalvation,</hi> and yet they refuſe the <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>light</hi> of this <hi>ſeeing</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>man,</hi> and upbraid him for being born in <hi>ſins</hi> and for going about to <hi>teach them,</hi> ſcorning that ſuch <hi>learned men</hi> as they ſhould be taught of ſuch as he was, though <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath made him <hi>learned,</hi> and given himſelfe for him.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon is rendered out of the words,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe ſuch are <hi>unlearned and unſtable ones:</hi> for as before we have ſeen ſuch perſons are <hi>deſtitute</hi> of the <hi>true learning,</hi> ſo alſo are they in an <hi>unſetled</hi> and <hi>unſtable condition,</hi> ſeeing as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.</note> witneſſeth <hi>that the Spirit is the eſtablisher;</hi> neither can they be <hi>rooted,</hi> and <hi>eſtablished in the Faith,</hi> according to the Apoſtles<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7.</note> ſaying, ſeeing they be not <hi>founded</hi> on the <hi>rock Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> but on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>ſands</hi> of <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> aryſing from a fleſhly mind, deſtitute of the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> for they have not <hi>learned, as the Truth is in Ieſus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> it muſt needs be ſo that ſuch muſt <hi>pervert the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> becauſe it is impoſſible for them to goe beyond their <hi>pronciple.</hi> Now their <hi>principle</hi> is <hi>errour,</hi> as the following words declare, and by it they be guided, and lead, even the whole heape of them, as bigge as it is, <hi>and theſe shall ſatisfie mens luſts, and turne them from the Faith, unto Fables,</hi> as the<note n="“" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.4.4.</note> Apoſtle long agoe hath foretold: For ſuch as are themſelves of the <hi>flesh,</hi> turn all things to <hi>fleshlineſſe,</hi> for that is it which they ſavour, for <hi>to the uncleane all things are uncleane, their Conſciences being defiled,</hi> as<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note> witneſſeth the Apoſtle: hence was it that whenas our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 2.29.</note> bade the Jewes to <hi>deſtroy this Temple</hi> meaning his<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>body,</hi> they themſelves being <hi>carnall,</hi> underſtood him to ſpeake of the <hi>Temple of Ieruſalem.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Capernaites,</hi> whenas <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> tells them, <hi>He will give</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>them of His flesh to eate,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>carnall</hi> cannot beare it, and all becauſe they be <hi>deſtitute</hi> of the <hi>Sririt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ</hi> 53.60.63. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.3.4.</note> for it was in a <hi>ſpirituall ſenſe</hi> that he intended it: And the like is to be ſeen in <hi>Nicodemus</hi> a Phariſee, and ſo a <hi>learned
<pb facs="tcp:4451:18"/>man,</hi> being a Teacher, and a Ruler of the Jewes, this man for all this whenas <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> tells him <hi>that he muſt be borne againe,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God,</hi> he ſeeing no further then into the <hi>naturall birth,</hi> demands how that could be, <hi>that a man when he is old should enter into his Mothers wombe, and be borne againe,</hi> ſo deſtitute was ne of the <hi>ſpirituall meaning</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Reaſon (me thinks) included in the words is,</p>
            <p>Becauſe ſuch Perſons are uſually <hi>veſſels of wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>prepared to deſtruction,</hi> therfore they drive all to the ſame end, to which themſelves belong: the <hi>Goſpell is the ſavour of life to life in them that are ſaved, but it is the ſavour of death to them that perish:</hi> Yet would I not from hence have any to conclude, that I deny <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion</hi> to <hi>learned men,</hi> as ſome in effect have affirmed (as I heare) of me, for the <hi>Scripture</hi> is againſt it, as is already before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.</note> Apoſtle, though there be <hi>not many.</hi> But yet this for certaine is the worſt worke that a <hi>carnall man</hi> can undertake, to meddle with the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſeeing that he abuſeth them, and that to his own <hi>deſtruction:</hi> for the <hi>word</hi> is a Sword with two edges, which whoſoever that is <hi>carnall</hi> meddles with, it will run into his <hi>heart,</hi> to<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>harden it againſt the day of wrath.</hi> And ſo I conceive the point is cleare, and plain, <hi>That men without Gods Spirit, though furnisht with Human-Learning, doe wreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their own deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> But here it will then be demanded, how ſhal we know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> or the <hi>ſpirit or Errour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, that the <hi>Spirit of God is a ſufficient witneſſe to it ſelfe,</hi> ſeeing that the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>Truth.</hi> Now this agreeing as it doth with the <hi>word,</hi> needs not any other <hi>teſtimony</hi> of it ſelfe, becauſe it is the <hi>witneſſe of God,</hi> and that is the <hi>greateſt,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Iohn, the</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit beareth witneſſe,</hi> for the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>Truth:</hi> and againe,<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>hereby we know that he abidoth in us, even by the Spirit that he hath given us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, it is to be known by its <hi>operations</hi> and <hi>works:</hi> as firſt it <hi>ſavours ſpirituall things, they that are after the flesh,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſavour the things of the flesh, and they that are after the Spirit, the things of the Spirit.</hi> And againe, <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit is life for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake,</hi> and is ſaid to be of a<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>quickning and an enlivening na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for righteouſneſſe.</hi> The fruits of it are further manifeſted in<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23.</note> other places. Now theſe things being ſound in us, do witnes for <hi>God</hi> againſt <hi>errour,</hi> though it ſet it ſelfe up with never ſo high a hand. And yet here (methinks) I heare the worldly
<pb facs="tcp:4451:19"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>learned men</hi> ſaying to me as did<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.24.</note> 
               <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> when went the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> from them to ſuch as I ſpeake of? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> To this I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That with <hi>Zedekiah</hi> ſuch perſons doe but begge the queſtion, and take for granted like him, that which they never had, for that could never depart from him which was never with him: therfore though he were <hi>great,</hi> and his <hi>companions many,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</note> as is ‡ ſhewed and that <hi>Micaiah</hi> was but one poore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet alone, and hate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the King, yet he had the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> whenas all the other were led and ruled by the <hi>lying Spirit;</hi> and though <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>learned ones</hi> cannot be beleeved of the great, and honourable Prophets of the world, but by <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiahs</hi> ſhall be ſmitten on the Cheek, when by them this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is demanded of the <hi>Lords</hi> Prophets, yet this anſwer may be given them, that whenas they come to hide themſelves in ſecret, and to be aſhamed of their <hi>viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and that the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>ſeaven laſt plagues</hi> come to be fulfilled, ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations;</hi> then they ſhall find the <hi>truth</hi> of the <hi>teſtimony</hi> that is borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, though in the meane time the <hi>ſervants</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> be committed to priſon, there <hi>to eate the bread of affliction, and the water of affliction</hi> for their <hi>teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> But though it be granted that <hi>Human Learning</hi> is no helpe to underſt and the mind of <hi>God,</hi> yet is it not uſefull to furniſh us with words to expreſſe our ſelvs in the delivery of the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwere with <hi>Paul,</hi> that the whole <hi>Scripture is given of God, and is profitable to make the man of God abſolute and throughly</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished to every good worke,</hi> whence I conclude, that if the <hi>Scripture be perfect, and abſolute for every good worke,</hi> then it is ſo for that, ſo that then there is no need of <hi>mans wiſdome</hi> to helpe the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God.</hi> And ſo yet further ſaith the Apoſtle, that he<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>preached the Goſpel not with wiſdome of words,</hi> if not with <hi>wiſdome of words,</hi> then I conclude, they were needleſſe, and ſo much the next words declare, <hi>leaſt</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I should make the Croſſe of none effect</hi> And againe, <hi>I, Bretheren,</hi> ſaith he <hi>when I came unto you, came not with the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>excellencie of words, or of wiſdome,</hi> ſhewing unto you the Councel of <hi>God,</hi> but frees himſelfe from it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that his <hi>preaching ſtood in the</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>inticing ſpeech of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but on the contrary, <hi>in the plaine evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit.</hi> And afterwards he gives the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</note> Reaſon for it, <hi>that their Faith should not be in the wiſdome of men,</hi> by which it ſeems it is ſubject ſo to be, if that were uſed. And ſo we find that indeed it is, and not in <hi>the power of God, by the plain demonſtation of the Spirit:</hi> and though in all this one would think the Apoſtle had
<pb facs="tcp:4451:19"/>ſaid enough in this matter for the manner of the delivering of the <hi>truth,</hi> yet for all this he hath not done with it, but minds it yet<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13.</note> againe, ſaying, <hi>Which things as we know them, ſo we alſo ſpeak not with words, which mans wiſdome teacheth.</hi> And ſo againe, he<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.19.</note> ſlightly paſſeth over the words of the <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> as not worth the knowing or regarding: therfore he ſaith, <hi>when he comes he will know, not their words, but their power.</hi> And ſo againe, he condiſcends to the <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> ſo farre, as to confeſſe <hi>that he was <note n="“" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.6.</note> rude in ſpeaking, but not ſo in knowledge:</hi> by all which places it plainly appeares, that <hi>mans wiſdome is to be rejected,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>ſpeaking the word of God,</hi> and that none are to affect any excellence that way, but to content themſelves even with the uſe of the <hi>naturall abilities</hi> they have, without any <hi>art</hi> or skill in <hi>learning</hi> further.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> But <hi>Apollas</hi> is ſaid to be an <hi>eloquent man,</hi> and <hi>mighty in the Scriptures, Acts</hi> 18.24.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> And ſo doubtles was <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> and thoſe mentioned in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. and yet, as I have before manifeſted, that whenas all theſe came to receive the <hi>faith</hi> they left, forſooke, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned all that: ſo do I beleeve was it here with this man, that whenas he came to be taught further in the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> that he then became more and more ſutable to the <hi>rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>ſimplicity of preaching the Goſpel,</hi> aſwell as <hi>Paul,</hi> for never afterwards do we reade that he was commended by that term, for ſuch manner of excellencie was proper to the <hi>Law,</hi> and not to the Goſpell in any degree But Secondly, take it for granted that he perſiſted in his <hi>eloquence,</hi> yet it appeares that it was ſuch as he had obtained by being <hi>mighty in the Scriptures:</hi> and this alſo further juſtifies a former Anſwer, <hi>that the Scripture alone is ſufficient to furnish us with expreſſion.</hi> So now the point remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>true</hi> for all this, <hi>That men deſtitute of the Spirit, having</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Learning, <hi>doe pervert the Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi> This in the firſt place may teach</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> All men, that are without <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> how <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> otherwiſe they ſeem to be, to beware of medling with the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> it is the worſt work that poſſibly they can undertake, for in ſo doing they meddle with that, in which they have no skill, and ſo wound themſelves: for it is a <hi>sharpe two edged ſword,</hi> and they having no skill to handle it, to be ſure it will dangerouſly wound them to their own deſtruction: but ſeeing the <hi>truth</hi> is ſo, as that they have neither <hi>eares to heare,</hi> nor <hi>hearts to underſtand it,</hi> therfore I will thus paſſe it over: and</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:20"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> In the next place, take notice that ſuch perſons without <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> whatever they be elſe, yet they be both <hi>unlearned</hi> and <hi>unſtable men,</hi> according to the <hi>mind</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> ſo the<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24</note> 
               <hi>unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> is called of <hi>Paul,</hi> an <hi>unlearned man:</hi> and ſo much in effect<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 1.6, 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> tells us, of a Faithleſſe mans <hi>inconſtancie,</hi> that <hi>he is toſt about like a wave,</hi> and is <hi>unſtable in all his wayes</hi> of Religion, for indeed wanting the <hi>Spirit</hi> to <hi>eſtablish</hi> him, he is driven hither and thither of every blaſt and breath of <hi>mans wiſdome,</hi> and ſo much experience, without any more <hi>Scriptures</hi> dayly proves, upon every change of <hi>orders,</hi> and <hi>ordinances of Religion:</hi> how confident have many <hi>wiſe worldly Learned men</hi> bin of their <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> for being brought to yeeld to this or that, when as the raging wave of the Sea hath roared but a <hi>little,</hi> how have theſe men fallen from their ſuppoſed <hi>ſtability</hi> and <hi>ſtedfaſtnes:</hi> ſo that inſtances I need not name, every ones ſmall experience can bring forth enough: but from all this there is given us to ſee the <hi>Scriptures</hi> fullfilled before our eyes, for our <hi>confirmation,</hi> and their juſt <hi>conviction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
               </label> Now in the next place, I will manifeſt in ſome few parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, how theſe <hi>learned men,</hi> but according to <hi>Peters intent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned men,</hi> do <hi>pervert the Scriptures,</hi> making their <hi>interpretations</hi> as <hi>carnall</hi> as themſelves, for whenas the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſpeake of <hi>learning,</hi> and ſo by it do for the moſt part commend unto us the <hi>learning</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> as before we have ſeen from this <hi>text,</hi> and many more places, theſe perſons preſently apply them to <hi>Human-Learning,</hi> and the <hi>texts</hi> are all by them wreſted and perverted: and in this kind many Inſtances might further be aledged. Firſt concerning the Church: whereas the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> doe authorize Chriſtians to <hi>gather themſelves together in Chriſts name,</hi> and ſo have the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>Gods preſence</hi> in ſo doing. This they preſently deny to be the <hi>intent</hi> of the place, and ſay it is to be meant of two or three come together in performance of <hi>prayer,</hi> or ſuch like, contrary to the ſcope of the place, which treats only of ſuch as are in <hi>Church-order,</hi> and have committed to them the <hi>power of binding and looſing,</hi> which the <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> his approving of the ſame by them; and beſides, where in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ſaid to be in the <hi>midſt</hi> of any, but his<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.11.12. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.16. <hi>Pſ</hi> 132.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Rev</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Churches:</hi> And further, whereas the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſpeake of the <hi>Church, Temple,</hi> and <hi>houſe of God,</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe ſavings to <hi>beleevers</hi> and ſuch as are<note n="§" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>with Heb.</hi> 3.6. <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>built upon Chriſt by faith,</hi> theſe they wreſt, and <hi>pervert</hi> in applying theſe <hi>titles</hi> to their <hi>houſes of lime and ſtone,</hi> calling them the <hi>houſes of God,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:4451:20"/>
               <hi>Temples</hi> for him to dwell in, though the <hi>Scriptures</hi> be plaine to the contrary, as <hi>Stephen</hi> declared to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.47. <hi>to</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>Councel</hi> long agoe, and that from the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.1.</note> 
               <hi>Prophet</hi> long before: and ſo our<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> denying for the time to come any ſuch places, as the Jewes, and the Samaritans doted on, but tells her, and us, that <hi>ſpirituall ſervice</hi> in<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>any place,</hi> as he ſaith himſelfe, ſhould pleaſe him, though it will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give carnall men content. Likewiſe are not the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> alledged frequently by theſe <hi>learned men:</hi> for the <hi>nation</hi> and <hi>people</hi> for being the <hi>Church of God,</hi> and for the ſame end, <hi>nationall obſervances,</hi> as an <hi>High Prieſt</hi> conſecrated and ſet apart for the <hi>ſervices</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſo under him the reſt of the <hi>holy Prieſts</hi> with their <hi>holy garments,</hi> and <hi>tythes</hi> and ſuch like for their maintenance, and for this purpoſe the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> alledged in a moſt plentifull manner, both from the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, for the juſtifying of their <hi>names, orders,</hi> and <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> whenas if it be <hi>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritually diſcerned,</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures</hi> not wreſted, nor <hi>perverted,</hi> it wilbe found true, as <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.14.15.</note> ſaith,<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. <hi>with Rev.</hi> 16.19.</note> that no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every Nation, nor any more any Nation, but <hi>in every Nation them that feare the Lord</hi> and none other, <hi>are accepted of him:</hi> Wheras <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelf hath told us, that the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 125. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>beaſt</hi> ſhould have <hi>power over every kindred, nation</hi> and <hi>tongue,</hi> and that the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Cities should fall:</hi> wheras <hi>Mount Sion</hi> the <hi>City of God</hi> ſhall never be <hi>moved,</hi> as ſaith the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Prophet,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> by this then it appeares that all ſuch <hi>Scriptures</hi> as are alledged for the maintenance of a <hi>Nationall Church</hi> are perverted. Seeing that long ſince the <hi>Lord</hi> hath rejected it, Now accounting a Company of <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>fellowship</hi> with himſelfe, to be <hi>Mount</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal.</hi> 14.9. <hi>from</hi> 6 <hi>to</hi> 9.</note>, that ſhall never be moved, and theſe he hath made<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>and</hi> 5.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Kings and Prieſts to God.</hi> The like we may ſee in the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church: ſeeing that they were of old time in that Church, to be honourable perſons, in outward honour and eſteem; for their names, <hi>Prieſts,</hi> for their <hi>callings,</hi> above the reſt of the people, <hi>a diſtinct body of themſelves;</hi> for their <hi>apparell,</hi> different in their <hi>adminiſtrations</hi> from other of the <hi>people;</hi> and ſo for their <hi>maintenance,</hi> by <hi>tythes,</hi> and <hi>offerings,</hi> all which had a reſpect to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and were in him to have their end, as the Apoſtle<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.12.</note> declares, as being but <hi>worldly rudiments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet theſe men, though they profeſſe themſelves <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and under the Goſpell, yet Childlike, as under <hi>tutors,</hi> and <hi>governours</hi> doe yet obſerve theſe things, after the <hi>rudiments</hi> of the world; and ſo ſutably to the Goſpell cannot
<pb facs="tcp:4451:21"/>abide to approve themſelves to be <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by ſuch <hi>marks</hi> as his <hi>word</hi> affords, as we have<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>to</hi> 10.</note> before conſidered, but they muſt be men of <hi>honour,</hi> and ſuch as be diſtinct from others in their <hi>apparell, maintenance,</hi> and ſuch like: <hi>dishonour,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach,</hi> and <hi>nakedneſse,</hi> and living on meere <hi>almes</hi> they cannot brook: but they be ſo farre from <hi>working with their own hands</hi> for their own <hi>neceſſities,</hi> as the Apoſtle requires that the<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.33, 34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of the Goſpell ſhould doe, as that they wreſt the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of the Law and the Prophets, haling in as it were by the <hi>hayre</hi> of the <hi>head,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to ſpeake for them and their <hi>delicious living, faring</hi> like <hi>Dives deliciouſly every day,</hi> wheras the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>feed the flock of God,</hi> not caring for it for <hi>filty lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, but of a ready mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving theſe things, and ſuch as theſe are which declare them to be more ſutable for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law, which tends unto <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>bondage,</hi> then ſuch as are Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and made partakers of the <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>ſervants</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> 
               <note place="margin">with the Anſwer.</note> I will ſpeake of ſome few things that are in difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them and us You know it is uſually objected againſt us becauſe of our departure, out of the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.68.</note> words of <hi>Peter</hi> to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> being theſe, <hi>Whether shall we goe, thou haſt the words of eternall life?</hi> from whence is concluded againſt us, if the <hi>text</hi> be not <hi>perverted,</hi> that we in leaving them doe forſake <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> wherin they take it for granted that He is with them, and not with thoſe that forſake them: wheras the <hi>text</hi> is cleare to prove, <hi>that the words of eternall life are in him,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> himſelfe ſaith alſo, <hi>the words that I ſpeake are ſpirit and life,</hi> and this who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but that <hi>he that hath the Son hath life, he that hath not the Sonne hath not life:</hi> But let not the <hi>text</hi> be wreſted, yet what proofe is here that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath the <hi>words of eternall life,</hi> and that there is no forſaking of him, and yet all that know wherin the difference lyes, know that this is the <hi>contraverſie,</hi> and how that theſe perſons thus forſaking goe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to the <hi>word of eternall life,</hi> ſeeing that the <hi>Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>binds the teſtimony and ſeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s up the Law among his Diſciples:</hi> ſo that till it can be proved that theſe leave <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and forſake the <hi>words of eternall life,</hi> the <hi>text</hi> muſt be taken for none other but to be <hi>perverted,</hi> and a vayle drawn over it to beguile the <hi>ſimple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Upon this ſame head hangs another great exception againſt us, <hi>Where we had our Converſion (if we have any) if not among them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſo taking it for granted, that we had it among them, a great outcry is made againſt us as if we had ſtolen their gods, and
<pb facs="tcp:4451:21"/>done them great wrong, and for this purpoſe this amongſt other things is alledged, that that Church which is able to beget is able to bring up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Now for Anſwer hereunto, it is to be minded that <hi>converſion</hi> doth properly belong to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.3.23.</note> 
               <hi>word of the Lord:</hi> Now this <hi>word</hi> by which we are all <hi>begotten</hi> is the proper <hi>portion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.</note> divers <hi>Scriptures</hi> declare: hence then muſt it needs follow, <hi>that whoſoever are converted to the Lord, thoſe by vertue of their converſion belong to the true Church,</hi> becauſe as is before ſaid, the <hi>word</hi> is hers, and therfore they are to cleave to her, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thoſe places, where they were <hi>converted,</hi> and that for this Reaſon, becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe is<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.6.</note> ſaid to <hi>count whenas he writes the people that this man was born there,</hi> that is, <hi>in Sion,</hi> the <hi>Church of God,</hi> though that the man were <hi>converted</hi> in <hi>mans ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> in <hi>Babel,</hi> and <hi>Paleſtina;</hi> yet the <hi>Lord</hi> when he <hi>counts,</hi> ſhall <hi>write</hi> the <hi>converted man</hi> to be <hi>born in Sion his Church:</hi> Now all <hi>Gods people</hi> ſhould <hi>count</hi> and <hi>write</hi> as <hi>God doth,</hi> and give <hi>Babel</hi> no <hi>honour</hi> at all of their <hi>converſion,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> doth not give her any; and the ſame thing is abundantly ſeen in the <hi>converts,</hi> that they are<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.40.</note> exhorted to leave thoſe places where they were <hi>converted,</hi> and ſo they did, as the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.44. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.4.34.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture</hi> manifeſts in many places, which might be noted.</p>
            <p>Againe it is to be minded that <hi>God</hi> himſelfe counts all the <hi>faithfull</hi> to belong to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Woman,</hi> the <hi>Church of God,</hi> as appeares in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> where the <hi>Man-child</hi> as is evident by<note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22.23.</note> other places containes all the <hi>faithfull,</hi> even the whole <hi>Church of God.</hi> This <hi>Son of God</hi> and his <hi>Man-child</hi> is called his<note n="‡̶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5, 1.</note> 
               <hi>people.</hi> The like appeares in <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.7, 8. where the <hi>Man-child</hi> is interpreted to be a <hi>whole Nation of Children,</hi> including all the <hi>faithfull.</hi> Now this <hi>woman</hi> is ſaid to be in <hi>travaile crying;</hi> and if yours be that <hi>Church</hi> that is in this <hi>travaile crying,</hi> and in <hi>pain</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I am content the <hi>Child</hi> ſhalbe acknowledged yours, but if it be in <hi>jollity,</hi> and without <hi>ſorrow,</hi> putting the others to <hi>pain,</hi> and ready to cut the <hi>living Child in pieces,</hi> how then can I acknowledge it for the <hi>true Mother,</hi> whenas alſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that Ieruſalem that is from above is the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Mother of us all,</hi> and ſhe is not one that <hi>gendereth</hi> to <hi>bondage,</hi> but to <hi>freedome,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle, and therfore me thinks it appeares that every ones <hi>converſion</hi> ſtrongly binds him to make ſpeed to that <hi>Church</hi> which conſiſts of ſuch as are <hi>faithfull in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being the proper inheritance to which they all belong, and to know that all ſuch places as are aledged to conclude otherwiſe, be but wreſted and <hi>perverted,</hi> though never ſo faire a gloſſe be ſet upon them;
<pb facs="tcp:4451:22"/>for <hi>God</hi> ever ſince the beginning hath <hi>put enmity betwixt the ſeed of the Woman and the ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> and accurſed ſhall all they be that ſhall joyne thoſe together that <hi>God</hi> hath ſo farre <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> and therfore let none of <hi>Gods ſervant</hi> ſtand with one foot on <hi>Mount-Sion,</hi> and another on <hi>Babylon,</hi> leaſt that which is <hi>halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> be turned out of the way. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> Another Objection againſt us is brought in the defence of your <hi>Miniſtry</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter this manner,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Miniſtry that doth the worke of the miniſtry of Ieſus Chriſt, ſpoken of in</hi> Epheſ 4. <hi>for the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfitting of the Saints, is a true Miniſtry, but your Miniſtry you ſay, doth the ſame worke,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Was it the <hi>worke</hi> of the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles, &amp;c. to read <hi>divine ſervice, Church Women Marry, and bury the dead,</hi> and ſuch like ſervices as there are? Did the Apoſtles <hi>perfit the Saints</hi> after this manner? For who knows not but that this is the ſubſtance of what your Office of Miniſtry binds you unto? as for preaching that may be diſpenced withall, and a little now and then may ſerve the turne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Beſides, as is granted, your Offices are not the ſame there mentioned that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt from on high gave gifts unto,</hi> for you have others, that the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks not any otherwiſe, then by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>names of blaſphemy:</hi> But for the power and worke of the Miniſtry, which you ſay is anſwerable to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, by your gathering of the Saints together, taking it for granted that you ſay, <hi>from what do you convert them?</hi> If from the <hi>power of darkneſſe,</hi> as you would ſeem to imply, into the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt,</hi> as<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</note> did the Apoſtle, then by your own grant in the <hi>power of darkneſſe you found them</hi> and the truth is, that where you found them there you leave them; when you found them before their <hi>converſion,</hi> you profeſſed of them that they were <hi>regenerate</hi> and <hi>born anew,</hi> to what then do you <hi>convert them?</hi> or have you <hi>converſion</hi> after <hi>regeneration?</hi> you alſo bade theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before, <hi>to take and eate in remembrance that Chriſt dyed for them,</hi> and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>give them the <hi>ſeales</hi> of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſalvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and yet after all this you being miniſters to them, come to juſtifie the truth of your <hi>Miniſtry</hi> by your <hi>converſion</hi> of theſe <hi>people,</hi> that have by theſe things no need of <hi>amendment,</hi> and yet when all is done that you plead for, they ſtill abide in the ſame <hi>Church,</hi> under the ſame <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> in the ſame <hi>worship</hi> that they were converſant in before, whenas I have declared before, that whenas the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>converted</hi> any, thoſe <hi>converts</hi> left their former places, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>dumb Idols to ſerve the living God.</hi> Now it hath been
<pb facs="tcp:4451:22"/>long ſince acknowledged and profeſſed, <hi>that the Worship of your Church, and the Miniſtry of it came out of the Popes shop,</hi> and muſt needs be reformed, or elſe the judgement of <hi>God</hi> cannot but light upon you, as hath bin manifeſted in the <hi>firſt and ſecond admonition to the Parliament in the dayes of Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and all know that yet it continues the ſame that then it was, and if it were ſo bad then, as it is reported that a thouſand <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſaid it was, ſmall cauſe have any to plead <hi>converſion,</hi> whenas they ſhall continue in ſuch <hi>abhominations,</hi> as that the plagues of <hi>God</hi> cannot by their own confeſſion be withheld: ſeeing that the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Spirit of God</hi> teacheth us, that the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.101.</note> 
               <hi>feare of the Lord teacheth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to refrain their feet from every evill way,</hi> and <hi>to cleanſe our ſelves from al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> filthineſse both of flesh and ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>to grow up unto full holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> or the <hi>worship of God,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1.</note> interprets it, and to <hi>hate the very</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>garment ſpotted by the flesh.</hi> Now theſe things well conſidered, it will appeare that the ſeveral <hi>Scriptures</hi> that are continually brought for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc of your Miniſtry, are but as ſo many flouriſhes by which the <hi>word of truth</hi> is wreſted and wringed like to a <hi>noſe of wax,</hi> contrary to their proper intents and ſcopes to ſerve your own turnes, which who they be of you or others that are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters of them, <hi>God</hi> knows, and one day will judge betwixt the <hi>righteous</hi> and the <hi>wicked</hi> and give to every one according as his workes ſhall be: In the mean while to me it appeares plain, that <hi>men deſtitute of Gods holy Spirit,</hi> be they as <hi>learned</hi> as may be in <hi>Mans-Learning,</hi> yet they do pervert all <hi>Scriptures</hi> to their own <hi>deſtruction,</hi> whenas the <hi>unlearned one,</hi> ſimple men and women having the <hi>Spirit of truth</hi> in them, ſhall rightly know them, and <hi>Gods mind</hi> in them for their great <hi>comfort.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, ſeeing this is ſo, that ſuch men do thus <hi>pervert</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> this ſhould provoke all that are made able <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> as ſaith the<note n="§" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2.</note> Apoſtle, that they take the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6.</note> adviſe, ſaying, <hi>if thou put the Bretheren in remembrance of theſe things thou shalt be a good Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> If thou put the Bretheren in remembrace of <hi>theſe things, What things?</hi> thoſe things mentioned<note n="‡̶" place="margin">from the <hi>1.</hi> verſe.</note> before, <hi>how that the Spirit hath foretold of Doctrines of Devils,</hi> how that men ſhould <hi>ſpeeake lyes through hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Zachary</hi> alſo foretold that the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.3.</note> Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of the Prophet ſhould ſay, <hi>that he told them lyes in the name of the Lord:</hi> If thou put the Bretheren in remembrance of theſe things, becauſe they are ſubject to <hi>forget</hi> them, and thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be their remembrancer, which if thou do thou ſhalt be a
<pb facs="tcp:4451:23"/>good <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which haſt bin nouriſhed up in the words of <hi>faith,</hi> and good <hi>doctrine;</hi> then marke, theſe things are not <hi>errors,</hi> nor <hi>lyes,</hi> nor he a <hi>falſe-teacher</hi> that ſpeakes of them, but a good <hi>Miniſter</hi> that hath bin <hi>nourisht up in faith, and good doctrine,</hi> which was continually taught of <hi>Paul,</hi> and heard of <hi>Timothy,</hi> and to this is to be added what the Apoſtle<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim</hi> 6.3.4.</note> ſaith further in this matter, declaring that he that <hi>conſenteth not to wholſome doctrine, that is according to godlines, is puft up, and knows nothing, but dotes about words,</hi> and is ſuch a one, as is ſo farre cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the <hi>flesh,</hi> as that he is to be ſeparated from: Therfore <hi>Gods good Miniſters,</hi> as we ſee, ſhould be carefull of theſe things as knowing of whom they ſhall receive their <hi>reward,</hi> and what ſhal alſo be their portion from men of the world in that which is<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>death in the world,</hi> but<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>life with the Lord: Be Faithfull therfore to the death, and you shall have a</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. 5 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>crown of life,</hi> declaring the power of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in you.</p>
            <p>Now in the laſt place, I will conclude with the <hi>exhortation</hi> of the<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.18.</note> Apoſtle in the words following, <hi>Ye therfore beloved ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ye know theſe things before,</hi> what things? among others thoſe, that <hi>worldly learned men</hi> are <hi>Gods unlearned men,</hi> being deſtitute of <hi>his Spirit,</hi> beware and take heed leaſt ye alſo aſwell as others (you being ſubject to it) be plucked away before you be aware into the <hi>errour</hi> of the <hi>wicked,</hi> to thinke that <hi>Gods Myſteries</hi> cannot be attained to by <hi>mans learning,</hi> and ſo you fall from your own <hi>ſtedfaſtnes,</hi> which is,<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>through Faith;</hi> for by <hi>Faith ye ſtand,</hi> and by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> for by it ye are alſo<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.</note> 
               <hi>eſtablisht:</hi> and for a preſervative againſt this <hi>errour,</hi> as oppoſite to it, <hi>grow and increaſe in the grace of God, and the knowledge of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which is that that will preſerve you from <hi>errour.</hi> Now to Him be <hi>glory,</hi> not to us, nor to Man, but to Him our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> both now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>I SAY 44.25.</bibl>
                  <p>The Lord fruſtrateth the tokens of the lyars, and maketh diviners mad, turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> foolishneſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4451:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
